<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Memory of that servant of God, John Story, revived shewing what manner of man he was from his youth to his grave, by the testimonies of several friends, to whom he was well known, and by whom, for his work sake in the truth, he was greatly beloved : to which is adjoyned something written by him, &amp;c., in his latter years, wherein his judgment is shewn concerning some particular things, and his great desires for love, unity, concord, and peace in the church of Christ.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 127 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50608</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1702</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19789</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13659725</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13659725</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101079</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50608)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101079)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 795:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Memory of that servant of God, John Story, revived shewing what manner of man he was from his youth to his grave, by the testimonies of several friends, to whom he was well known, and by whom, for his work sake in the truth, he was greatly beloved : to which is adjoyned something written by him, &amp;c., in his latter years, wherein his judgment is shewn concerning some particular things, and his great desires for love, unity, concord, and peace in the church of Christ.</title>
                  <author>Wilkinson, John, d. ca. 1683. Brief relation concerning the life and death of John Story.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Gain ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"A brief relation concerning the life and death of John Story / by John Wilkinson": p. 4-8.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 46.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Story, John, d. 1681.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Biography.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101079:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE MEMORY Of that Servant of God, <hi rend="blackletterType">Iohn Story, Revived.</hi> Shewing,</p>
            <p>What manner of Man he was from his Youth to his Grave, by the Teſtimonies of ſeveral Friends, to whom he was well known, and by whom (for his Work ſake in the Truth) he was greatly Beloved.</p>
            <p>To which is adjoyned ſomething written by him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in his latter years, wherein his Judgement is ſhewn concerning ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar things; and his great deſires for <hi>Love, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, Concord</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> in the Church of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Tree is not ſo well known by Reports as by its Fruits.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Having a good Conſcience, that whereas they ſpeak evil of you, as of evil-doers, they may be aſhamed, that falſly accuſe your good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation in Chriſt,</hi> 
                  <bibl>1 Pet. 3. 16.</bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Righteous ſhall be in everlaſting Remembrance, yea his Righteouſneſs endureth for ever: The wicked ſhall ſee it, and be grieved, he ſhall gnaſh with his teeth and melt away: The deſire of the wicked ſhall periſh,</hi> 
                  <bibl>Pſal. 112.</bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>I am a Man of Peace, but when I ſpeak; they are for War,</hi> 
                  <bibl>Pſ. 120. 7.</bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Gain,</hi> Living in the Upper <hi>Moor-Fields,</hi> near the <hi>Flying-Horſe,</hi> M. DC. LXXXIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:101079:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:101079:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>ALthough nothing can now be added to, or diminiſhed from the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Happineſs of our Deceaſed Friend, <hi>John Story,</hi> yet ſince his Departure out of this World; it came into the Hearts of ſome to Write ſomething concerning him: and knowing that a thing of this nature, hath not only been expected, but long ſince earneſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired by many honeſt Friends in Divers parts of this Nation: It is now for their ſakes, and others to whom it may be ſerviceable, made Publick. Thou haſt here a Relation of the Life and Death of that Faithful Servant of the Lord, in the following Teſtimonys of ſeveral Friends, to whom he was very well known; and being now at Reſt from all his Labours, is bleſſed with them which dye in the Lord, thus its witneſſed of him; about whom many did concern themſelves, ſome for the better, and others for the worſe; like to thoſe, who in the dayes of our Lord Chriſt, when ſome ſaid of him he is a good Man, others ſaid nay, but he deceiveth the People and hath a Devil. And this many did through ignorance, condemn the juſt one. And when we conſider what gainſaying, reproaches and contradictions our dear Friend <hi>J. S.</hi> met with in his Pilgrimage, and the Patience God indued him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and what Charitable conſtructions he would make of Injuries offered to him, &amp;c. it may truly be ſaid, He was a Man of Peace: and he had this ſaying often with him <hi>(viz.) That the long-ſuffering of the Saints would have an end;</hi> Exhorting Friends to patience in well-doing. We for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear (as yet) to write what many could ſay more particularly concerning him; Recommending what here follows to thy ſerious and impartial peruſal, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring that prejudice may not blind the eye of thy underſtanding, and hinder thee from reaping that benefit intended.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:101079:3"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Brief Relation concerning the Life and Death of <hi>John Story,</hi> by <hi>John Wilkinſon.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>JOHN STORY, deſcended of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Parents in <hi>Weſtmorland,</hi> and they lived honeſtly, (having Land, Goods and Trade) in good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute amongſt their Neighbours; and he was well Educated in his Youth, and through his diligence grew able in pronunciation of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue. He was never ſeen inclinable to any evil Vice, but againſt all ſuch things from his Youth; neither could he endure any crooked ways, or croſſneſs in a Family, but ſhewed his diſlike thereof, and the Gift of God in him did ſo prevail, that in his Childhood he had a wonderful ſenſe of the Wo and Wrath that would come upon the Wicked, and an opening of Joy and Peace to the Righteous.</p>
               <p>In his Youth I know none in theſe Parts to exceed him in Godlineſs, for the Fear of God had the chief Room in his Heart, and he had a great regard to keep his Commands; and a wonderful Knowledge God gave unto him, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering his Day and Age, ſtill ſeeking more and more the Knowledge of God, and the way of his Kingdom; his Life anſwered his inward Knowledge, and at the age of ten Years he could not joyn with any in wanton Sports, Games and Plays, which made many to wonder: notwithſtanding that, the inward Knowledge which God gave unto him, did ſo prevail with him, that not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the vanity of ſuch things, was diſcovered to him, but he was alſo begotten of God into an abhorrence thereof, judging it a miſpent and loſt time: and when he was grown to twelve years of Age, his great enquiry was, where to find a Place and People that ſought the Lord; for the Word of God in his Heart did powerfully quicken his Soul to Life.</p>
               <p>And Breathing, and Praying in private and publick; and when he found a People ſeeking the Lord, it was great Joy to his Soul, and he was ready prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to joyn with ſuch as had Openings by the inviſible Spirit of God, namely, ſuch as <hi>Gervis Benſon, Francis Howgil, Edward Burrough, John Audland, Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Hubberthorn,</hi> &amp;c. and many more in <hi>Weſtmorland</hi> prepared of God for the Service of Truth, in, and unto whom God, in the Fulneſs of Time, reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Son, and by his Spirit anointed them Miniſters of the Everlaſting Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, to Preach the Glad-tydings of Salvation, with many more in ſundry Parts of this Nation (an unutterable Bleſſing to a People and Kingdom) among whom <hi>John Story</hi> alſo was Anointed to Preach the Goſpel. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101079:3"/> his Call forth into other Countries, he was brought up in the Knowledge of Husbandry, and was skilful in that Work, and alſo laborious and careful, and joyned himſelf with Families that feared God, and ſought him with all their Hearts; he had in his young Years ſuch a Gift of Prayer, which the Seekers after God had a great Love unto; and his chief Delight was in ſuch Company: he Hungred and Thirſted after Righteouſneſs (a State bleſſed of God) who filled him with many Vertues, and made him, even in his Youth, an Inſtrument of much Good, by his holy Converſation and good Example; and God gave him the Knowledge of many weighty and glorious Things of his Kingdom; and he had a holy Zeal to preſs all unto Righteouſneſs; and Preached in Publick Aſſemblies in <hi>Weſtmoreland,</hi> and Places adjoyning about the Age of fourteen Years, and depended on the Gift of God for his Openings and Doctrine, being of a loving Carriage to all People, beyond many that now profeſs more Knowledge, and boaſt of high Things in theſe latter Days: he ſaw with the Openings of God in that Day, <hi>That all Made Forms Men placed Religion in, were not only empty and dry, without Vertue and Life, but alſo a Snare, and of evil Effect:</hi> and could not joyn to any ſuch; but to exerciſe and practiſe according to inward Knowledge given of God; ſaying, <hi>That leads juſtly in a holy manner of Life: but Embarking into made Forms, and placing Religion in them, expecting Bleſſings from them; made it juſt with God to ſhut up Heaven, to hide his Glory, and keep hid the Things of his Kingdom: But depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon God, fits People, and prepares for his Service, and gives the true Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of what he requires to Practice.</hi> His Saying hath been, <hi>That even to him in that Eſtate was the Son of God Revealed, the Great and Wonderful Power of the Almighty, the Everlasting Day of Life, the Higheſt Power, the Commander and Giver of his Word, he that appeared in the Clouds of Heaven, opening glorious Things, hath Revealed himſelf in Power and great Glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though he was a Man, in his Life, that would not willingly miſs the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Attainments in Truth, yet he was not aſhamed of being ſilent, when in the Preſence of an Aſſembly; for the Day was, wherein he ſaw the King, the Lord of Hoſts, whoſe Majeſty made him aſtoniſhed, at whoſe Preſence and Sight he was ſtruck ſilent for the ſpace of a whole Year, becauſe he then ſaw that the Openings of God was Preached by him, judging his inward Eſtate and Knowledge far ſhort of the wonderful Knowledge and excellent Glory, when he appeared in Fulneſs: and ſo he waited in ſilence many a Meeting, and thought himſelf unfit to Preach his Excellency and Greatneſs, ſuffering Famine, and ſitting under the Sword (which the Word, by which all Things were made, is compared unto) in a ſenſe of the true Croſs and right Humility that goes before true Honour, waiting for the Movings of the Almighty, and his Spirit to demonſtrate the Way of Life; and ſaid, <hi>He was not Condemned of God in falling ſhort of anſwering the Knowledge given unto him; but far ſhort in declaring the greatneſs of his Power and Fullneſs. It is not you that ſpeak</hi> (uſing the words of Chriſt) <hi>but the Spirit of my Father that ſpeaketh in you.</hi>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:101079:4"/> This was the manner of his Life till God gave him the Word, and called him forth; for he ſaid, <hi>If I had ſate in Silence all my Life, I durſt not go before God ſpake by his Spirit in me.</hi> And truly Gods Power and Preſence was with him, and his Word and Motion plentifully given unto him, and Wiſdom from above to divide the Word aright, and God made his way to proſper, that the People prepared of God with his inviſible Spirit, anſwered the Word as Face anſwereth Face in a Glaſs, and many that had miſt their way to God, by ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him without; he turned to the Light and Appearance of Chriſt within; and he was confirmed in the Word through the Power and Effect thereof, and Sealed to God in his Service, who gave him great Ability to fulfil his Miniſtry. He had but a very weak Body, and travelled on foot <hi>North</hi> and <hi>South</hi> in this Nation about the ſpace of three years, I being his Companion, do well know it; and great Colds, after much heat in <hi>Meetings,</hi> empaired his Health, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides his Concern with many Oppoſers in the breaking forth of Truth, cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing many long and tedious Diſputes; in which his Moderation in Gods Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom greatly appeared, labouring in Truth to convince the Gainſayers: he had great Skill and Ability given of God, (<hi>Viz.</hi>) in Diſputes, that <hi>his Bow still abode in Strength,</hi> and the Contenders for their Imaginations, and againſt the Truth, fell before him, he was ſo ſtrengthened with the Arm of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God of <hi>Jacob,</hi> who honoured his Truth with him in the Sight of many Aſſemblies, the Contenders often confeſſing to his Moderation and Meekneſs; notwithſtanding, if he got hold of Deceit and falſe Affirmations (from wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Oppoſers) he held ſuch very hard to the Point, not letting them go to another thing, unleſs they confeſt their Errour, but any <hi>Objection</hi> or <hi>Doubt</hi> through Ignorance was meekly in Truth reſolved, and he had no delight to diſpute with Oppoſers, or high Contenders, unleſs they themſelves were the Cauſe, neither to ſpread in Writing or Print, any Diſputes, though often deſired.</p>
               <p>And at that time many longed to hear the Word of God, and cryed, <hi>Come and have a Meeting with us:</hi> and ſometimes went to help, but even as <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Macedonia,</hi> by Viſion and Revelation, to Preach the Goſpel to them, and viſiting over and over them to whom God ſent him to Preach the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>He was faithful in Doing or in Suffering as required of the Almighty, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs his Sufferings in <hi>Saliſbury Goal,</hi> under Sentence of <hi>Premunire,</hi> almoſt a whole year, but delivered at the Kings <hi>Coronation:</hi> for before Preſcriptions, Outward Orders and Forms among ſome Friends were ſo Impoſed, and carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a ſtreſs of Religion, <hi>John Story</hi> was not judged a Flyer in Perſecution, but eſteemed honourable among the Brethren; and it is plain, that becauſe he could not receive ſome Preſcriptions of Men's, with all its Formalities, therefore was he Proceeded againſt (by ſome) <hi>as one of a wrong Spirit, and out of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity;</hi> though he oppoſed not others therein, if they were ſo perſwaded of God: but they would not be ſatisfied with that, but oppoſed him in Publick Meetings, as <hi>one that hated to be Reformed;</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:101079:4"/> Alas! Alas! his Religion was not formed with Orders and Precepts of Men, he could not ſo far diſhonour his God, nor judge any Friends ſo weak in Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding to make a Breach of Unity with them under pretence of Motion, Government and Dignity: <hi>John</hi> ſaid, <hi>He was often aſhamed of ſuch a Degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration:</hi> and ſaid, <hi>if it did continue, the evil Effects would ſcarcely ceaſe.</hi> He rendred not evil for evil, by oppoſing his Oppoſers in Meetings for Publick Worſhip, but exhorted to Righteouſneſs and Peace, and if that could not be born, <hi>it be ſpeaketh</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>a Famine of the Word.</hi> Oh he was ſound in Judgment, and not afraid that his Doctrine ſhould come to publick view: his Candle was lighted, not to put under a <hi>Buſhel:</hi> let them that have oppoſed him, and endeavoured to darken the light and ſhining thereof through him, look to it; Repent and turn to God before it be too late, leaſt God ſuffers the ſame meaſure to be meted again, for his Ways are Equal and Juſt, and Righteous altogether; and as he endeavoured his Doctrine ſhould be tryed, commending it to every mans Conſcience in the Sight of God; ſo alſo his proceeding and good Works, ſaying, <hi>How ſhould Men glorifie our Heavenly Father, if our Proceedings and good Works be hid from them; and if People wait not in the Spirit, but oppoſe it with Forms of Mans making, ſuch cannot reliſh the Word of Life, nor ſuffer Truth's Teſtimony in Quiet, but cauſeth jangling with Forms in the break of the Day, againſt Truth, and ſee not the Glory that excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, nor the Teſtimonies that exalts the Light, which God commanded to ſhine forth in the Face of Jeſus, whom the Righteous loveth, and is their Life, in which my dear Companion,</hi> J. S. <hi>had great Delight.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He was a loving and plain Man, and greatly abhorred Feignedneſs, warning People that they ſhould not worſhip the Works of their own hands, nor feign <hi>Humility,</hi> and cautioned to beware of <hi>a Spirit of Pride,</hi> and ſeeking <hi>Honour and Greatneſs;</hi> which he ſaw in his day, was too much ſought after. When he heard ſuch Doctrine, <hi>Viz. Have an Eye to the Brethren,</hi> it ſeemed ſtrange and new, not like Truth, as the proceedings about Outward Orders did; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring the Doctrine before, was, <hi>Look unto the Lord, and eye him:</hi> and, <hi>The Wiſemans Eye is in his Head;</hi> Spiritually meaning in Chriſt. However, what was meant by <hi>having an Eye to the Brethren,</hi> they beſt know who have uſed it; but <hi>John Story</hi> in his Life, had a great Diſlike of it, doubting to what it would grow; he profeſt not much diſcerning in making an outward ſhew with his Eyes, but he had a pure diſcerning with the Light of the Spirit in the Elect Eſtate in Chriſt; Satan transformed into an Angel of Light, nor his Miniſters appearing as the Miniſters of Righteouſneſs, could not deceive him, nor feigned Flattery, nor Sheeps Cloathing hide the Ravening <hi>Wolf</hi> from his Sight, nor make him conclude with Threatnings, that falſe Accuſations and unrighteous Judgment was of the <hi>Lamb</hi>'s Nature: truly the worth of ſuch a Miniſter of Truth cannot be equalled with outward Treaſure; and ſuch ſent of God is a Bleſſing to a Kingdom, or a Nation, but being rejected and oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, will ſurely bring a Curſe; but no Diſturbers could move him, but in all
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101079:5"/> his Sufferings God endued him with Patience, though many times in great weakneſs of Body, and often in appearance nigh unto Death.</p>
               <p>But the Prophecy of the badneſs of his Life in 1676, is now proved as falſe as <hi>Solomon Eccles</hi> Prophecy is, of the Time of his Death; for ſome years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that, God gave him Strength, and carryed him hundreds of Miles in his Service: afterwards he was very weak, at which time a Friend (a Doctor, <hi>George Walker</hi>) came to viſit him, and I heard him ſay, <hi>He was near gone to all outward Appearance, unleſs God had ſome further Work for him to do.</hi> And indeed the Almighty, into whoſe Hand he was committed, raiſed him up again, and carryed him <hi>South</hi> and <hi>Weſt,</hi> Strengthening and Comforting the Brethren, till his Teſtimony was finiſhed in thoſe Parts, whoſe loſs is great, and Cauſe of ſorrowing, that they ſhall ſee his Face no more; for the Lord brought him to <hi>Weſtmoreland,</hi> his Native Country, where he was received with great Gladneſs, for the Lords Power and Preſence was with him, to the great Refreſhment of the truly Righteous, and on a <hi>Firſt-day</hi> at a Meeting in <hi>Ken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal,</hi> cleared his Conſcience in Teſtimony to the Antient Truth, in which his Doctrine was wonderful weighty, and his Experience very great.</p>
               <p>He was but young as to number of years, between fourty and fifty, but he fulfilled a great time, if Wiſdom be Gray-hair, and undefiled Life, old Age; he was weak of Body about two weeks, not able to go abroad, but little com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of Sickneſs; the gentle Dealings of the Lord was wonderful to him, and brought many to remember his meek Behaviour; and Neighbours ſaid, he lived well, and was like to dye well; he was like an innocent Lamb, opened not his mouth to complain, the merciful Dealings of God unto him at all times filled him with a great ſenſe of Joy and true content, having aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to reſt with him, the Fountain of Life and Fulneſs, which through (but) a meaſure of his Spirit, ſuch Heavenly Joy and true Content cometh. And he ſeeing his Teſtimony and Time on Earth was finiſhed, his great Love he ſignified to all Friends in Truth, while he had Strength to ſpeak, deſiring God to preſerve them in it to the End; and lay ſilent a pritty while, moving his hands (as I took it, while with him) in a ſenſe of Reſt and Heavenly Praiſe; after that, I had not been two hours from him (which was on ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent occaſion) till word came to me, he was Departed.</p>
               <closer>So much concerning his Innocent Life, and part of Trouble he met with, for his Teſtimony to Truth, his Meekneſs and Content, and Aſſurance of Eternal Felicity, as duely obſerved about the manner of his Departure, by
<signed>John Wilkingſon.</signed>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:101079:5"/>
                  <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
                  <p>I Have this farther to add, that <hi>John Story</hi> is gone to his Reſt, whoſe Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony when God Revealed his Son in him, was given in Gods power, and would have ſitten in Silence without he Revealed the Word of Life: and to all unprejudiced hearers that thirſted after Righteouſneſs, and that Knowledg and Power that leadeth to Happineſs; his Doctrine dropt as the Rain, that Refreſheth the tender Graſs, to all thriſty and longing ſouls, to their great refreſhment and conſolation; and my Counſel to all op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers of the Miniſters of Truth is, that they ceaſe for time to come, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and let no more ſlanderers have place to beget prejudice, in you, but let the Truth you profeſs be your defence againſt it. And with your own mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures ſavour for your ſelves, leaſt you be led in a falſe belief by men that love and luſt to rule, under pretence of Gods motion and unbrotherly proceedings, under pretence of Church Power be ſlow in ſpeaking without certain knowledge, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally evil of anytill your own experence with Truth prove it to you, through your exact tryal, leaſt you be lead by Men into a falſe Faith, to ſpeak evil of true Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers and condemn them to be of a wrong ſpirit whom God Juſtifieth; and if this counſel had been followed, and was the Doctrine of Truth in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining, <hi>to your own, to your own,</hi> the difference among Friends had been kept in a narrow compaſs, and but a few concerned that cauſed difference, and the things but Temporal, which Spiritual Weapons would ſoon have conquered and overcome, and Truth, Peace, and ſtablity would have abounded; then high places with ſpiritual wickedneſs had not been aſſumed; but when temporal things hath Religion placed in them (which only ſprings form the Fountain of Life) this diſhonours God who is the Author of all true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) And makes it a ſhelter for the greateſt Hypocrites and even a Cage for all unclean Birds to Chatter againſt the Righteous that receive the Word of Truth, and both live, and practice as their Meaſures of God Requireth, and agreeable to the Scriptures of holy Men who are gon to their Reſt, where nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther falſe Witneſs nor unrighteous Judgment can take away their Inheritance.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>I. W.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt_from_letter">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:101079:6"/>
               <head>Something taken out of a Letter from George Dodgſon (to a friend) bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing date the twenty ſeventh of the ninth Month, 1681. concerning the departure of <hi>John Story.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THat which I have to communicate to thee and Friends, and which is to the Sadening and Sorrow of many hearts, is the departure of our Dear Brother <hi>I. S.</hi> who in much peace and quiet departed this Life the laſt third day, having no ſenſe of Paine upon him, to the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of Friends but even as though he had Slumbered very Quietly, breathed his laſt. He had been out of health about fourteen dayes before, but not very likely for Death till about four dayes before he dyed, when the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper and Weakneſs ſeized more fully upon him: He was Intrerred very honourably, a great many People being there preſent, both of Friends and of the Neighbourhood: And as he in his Life time, was of a grave and reverent Deportment, even ſo was he accompanyed to his Grave, People generally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moning his death, but the Hearts of Friends was generally filled with ſorrow, and their Eyes with Teares, by reaſon of that inward affection they bare unto him, as alſo the great ſenſe of the great Loſs they ſuſtained in his Death, who hath been a living example of Righteouſneſs amongſt us, both in Life and Doctrine, even in a manner from his Child-hood, as if he had been Choſen from the Womb, and Sanctified for a Veſſel of honour and as he often exhorted o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, to continue walking in the way of Truth, that in the latter end they might attain and come more fully to poſſeſs the Joyes of the everlaſting King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, where all the Troubles and Sorrows of this preſent Life ſhall be wiped away, and come to an end. So Doubtleſs he is now entred into the full fruiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe never-fading Joyes wherein all the ſorrow and ſighing and Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of this preſent Life is come to an end, and is Aſcended out of the reach of wicked Tongues and Pens: But what can be ſaid, Doubtleſs God endued him with Divine Wiſdom to a large degree, and accompanyed him with his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Power and Preſence, in Declaring the way of Life, and opening the Miſteries of the Kingdom to the comfort and Conſolation of many who now mourn in Secret for his abſence; and I fear that time to come may know the want of ſuch, and I alſo fear that many in this preſent time have alſo rendred themſelves unworthy of ſuch: but I deſire we may make a good uſe of theſe things, and that we look to our own ſtanding, and that we may walk accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the exhortations and counſel delivered unto us both by him, and other his faithful Companions, which have anſwered the Truth in our own hearts.</p>
               <p>There was a very good opportunity for <hi>J. W.</hi> and others to bear a Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to Truth, and the People gave very Diligent attention while he exhorted and Counſeled to follow thoſe things that make for peace and brings to reſt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101079:6"/> in the latter end, clearly Demonſtrating the way thereunto; with ſuch things further as opened in him, ſuitable upon that occaſion.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>G. D.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="testimony">
               <head>The Teſtimony of <hi>John Jennings,</hi> by way of Preface, to the following Teſtimonies of ſeveral Friends in <hi>Wiltſhire.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Courteous and Friendly Readers,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>BE It known unto you, that what is here written by way of Lamentation &amp; Teſtimony of our Deceaſed Friend <hi>John Story,</hi> is not to draw forth the Minds of any for to admire him or any other Inſtrument that the Lord may make uſe of for the good of any Perſon or People, but that which is here written, is truly to certify all friendly People, unto whom it may come, what manner of Life, Doctrine and Converſation, this our deceaſed Friend did Live, and Declare whilſt he was amongſt us; and if any through envy or prejudice, either againſt him or any of us, doth or ſhall endeavour to gainſay, oppoſe or invalidate this our Teſtimony concerning him, we doubt not but that by Gods aſſiſtance we ſhall be throughly enabled for to Vindicate the ſame againſt any Oppoſers hereof; for we know that what is here written of him, is what is true, and according to the beſt of our knowledge; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed we had rather come ſhort of commending any Perſon, rather than to praiſe or commend any beyond their due deſerts. But foraſmuch as it hath ſo happened that this worthy Man, and Servant of God, hath been by ſome too much abuſed in his Chriſtian Reputation, and miſ-repreſented as an Apoſtate, or <hi>Dark and Creeping Spirit,</hi> it was ſo much the more on ſome of our Spirits for to give, forth this following Teſtmony, that as friends might truly know what he was amongſt us, and what Juſt Cauſe we had truly to love and eſteem him as a ſervant of Chriſt even unto the laſt, and truly as the power and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God was with him in his Miniſtry in former years, when he was generally well ſpoken of by moſt or all that did love the Truth in theſe parts, So we can truly ſay that at the laſt Meeting which he had in this Country the Lord did appear by him and through him as in former times unto the Edifie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Comforting of his People and we had a very good and comfortable Meeting, and therefore if any have let in any Prejudice or hard thoughts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, becauſe they may have heard an evil report of him; we do ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe ſuch to be more carful how they do receive Reports, and let in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice againſt any of Gods ſervants, leaſt they do there by hurt themſelves and break their own Inward Peace: and as concerning others, who have villified this ſervant of God either by their hard ſpeeches or Writings againſt him, it
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101079:7"/> is with us to adviſe ſuch for to Repent of what they have already done, and to learn to do ſo no more, leaſt they are found fighters againſt God and his faithful ſervants, and in thus doing we have thus far cleared our Conſciences towards all ſuch and ſhall leave the effect thereof unto God, and deſire all thoſe that Read the following Teſtimony for to Read it without Prejudice or Carping at what is written, but to read it as in Gods fear, and with a ſerious and conſiderate mind, that ſo they may the better underſtand what they read, and conſider of it.</p>
               <p>If any ſober and moderate Inquirer that is yet Ignorant of the matter ſhould ask or inquire of us what was the ground or cauſe wherefore the ſaid <hi>J. S.</hi> have been ſo miſrepreſented as an <hi>Apoaſtate</hi> and a <hi>dark</hi> and <hi>creeping ſpirit,</hi> if he was ſuch an honeſt man as you ſeem to ſignifie? To this we ſhall give in ſhort this Anſwer: That as far as we could yet ever underſtand the Real ground and cauſe of it was, becauſe he did not ſo far conform and ſubmit unto the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up, and eſtabliſhing of ſome outward Orders and Ceremonys amongſt Friends and as ſome that did, (or yet doth) profeſs the Truth would have had him to have done: and if any ſhould yet inquire, why he did not ſubmit un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to others for Unities ſake. To this we Anſwer, that this Queſtion might more properly have been propoſed unto him in his Life time, and if it had been ſo Propoſed, doubtleſs he would have given a ſound and proper Anſwer there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto: yet forasmuch as he is gone and cannot now Anſwer for himſelf, we do believe that we may truly give this Anſwer on his behalf (<hi>viz.</hi>) That it was for conſcience ſake that he could not, or did not Conforme and ſubmit unto the ſetting up ſuch Orders and Ceremonies as others would have had him to have don and douptleſs he thought them to be ſuperfluous and more then was Really needful, for to be ſo ſtrictly practiced amongſt Gods People, and that this was the Real ground and Cauſe wherefore he hath been ſo Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniated and miſ-repreſented, we have caſe to believe for theſe following Reaſons.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt.</hi> Becauſe he was alwayes owned and eſteemed as a ſervant of Chriſt and a true Miniſter of the Goſpel, by ſuch as did profeſs the Truth, as far as ever we did underſtand: until ſuch time as he did object againſt or diſlike with the ſetting up of ſuch outward Orders and Ceremonies as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>2dly.</hi> Becauſe that ſince that time he did miſlike ſuch things as aforeſaid we have found that there hath been endeavours by ſome to undervalue him, and his Teſtimony, and occaſions ſought againſt him, to render him as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy and contemplible as poſſible they could.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>3ly.</hi> Becauſe ſome of us concerned in the following Teſtimonies have often asked of thoſe who have been Oppoſers, at leaſt Diſlikers of him, what they had againſt him of evil, either in his Life, Converſation or Doctrine, to lay to his charge: and it hath been ſaid unto ſuch, that if they could make any thing of evil appear in him either in Life, Converſation, or Doctrine, that then we would diſown him: But inſtead of proving any thing of evil
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101079:7"/> againſt him, it hath been oftentimes anſwered after this manner, <hi>That as to his Life and Converſation it was honest, or they had nothing againſt him for that; and as to his Doctrine, it was good Words, but that they did not come from a Right Spirit.</hi> Or to that effect.</p>
               <p>And therefore ſince his Oppoſers did not prove any thing of this nature againſt him while he was Living, we ſhall think our ſelves, or any others, not much obliged to believe any thing of evil Report that others may ſay of, or concerning him now he is Removed from <hi>amongſt Men:</hi> and if any ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to defame him in his <hi>Christian Reputation</hi> now he is gone, doubtleſs it will rather ſeem to us, or any ſober and moderate People, <hi>to ſavour of a Spirit of Malice and Prejudice, than of the Spirit of Christianity or common Civility:</hi> but if any of his Oppoſers ſhould think, that out of fear we do, as it were, beſpeak their Silence, we do ſay to ſuch, let them do as they pleaſe, for we fear them not.</p>
               <p>We further ſay, we have obſerved, <hi>That not one Man we know of, who hath a Publick Teſtimony, and doth not Conform unto Orders and Ceremonies, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, that is now owned or accounted of as formerly, by thoſe who have appeared againſt him, or are Hot and Zealous for the Orders,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And although ſuch Nonconformiſts are as blameleſs in their Lives and Converſations, and as Sound in their Doctrine and Teſtimonies as formerly, yet we find that they are either pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly Diſowned, or elſe privately Calumniated and Diſliked withal.</hi> And on the other hand we have likewiſe obſerved, <hi>That if others who are Conformable, and Preach up the Orders,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>are guilty of ſuch things as in Truth cannot be juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, yet ſuch Perſons are either Owned, or at leaſtwiſe not publickly reproved, that we know of.</hi> And therefore we do ſay unto ſuch, as do thus turn Juſtice and true Judgment backwards, and endeavour to ſmother over the Errours (either in Doctrine or Life and Converſation) of the Guilty, and to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn the Innocent, becauſe of their Nonconformity; beware, leaſt you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke the Lord to Wrath, and he doth break forth amongſt you in his ſore Diſpleaſure.</p>
               <p>And if any Friendly Reader ſhould ſuppoſe that the Publication of this Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face and following Teſtimonies may give occaſion for a further Contention, becauſe ſome things therein may ſeem to reflect ſomewhat hard in General on ſuch as were Oppoſers or Diſlikers of him, and ſo for that reaſon the Reader (who loves to be quiet, and deſires that all Contentions amongſt Friends were at an end) doth diſlike the Publication hereof.</p>
               <p>To which it may be anſwered, That after the Deceaſe of <hi>J. S.</hi> it reſted on the Spirits of ſeveral Friends (in ſeveral Places and Countries where he had Miniſtred and been Serviceable) to write ſomething concerning him, and what Service he had done for the Lord amongſt them in his Day and Time: and among the reſt, it came upon ſome of us in <hi>Wiltſhire,</hi> to publiſh a Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny after this manner, by way of Lamentation for the Loſs of ſo able a Preacher of Gods Truth, as he was in his Day and Time, and alſo to give ſome ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101079:8"/> of what he was amongſt us, and what he did ſtand for and againſt, that ſo thoſe who had heard of him, and not known him by face, might be truly informed of his Doctrine, Life and Converſation among us who were well acquainted with him for many years, and ſo have had the more Experience thereof. But foraſmuch as ſeveral Friends who were Conſcientiouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned to Write, did live (ſome of them) far diſtant one from the other, it hath been the more trouble to collect their ſeveral Teſtimonies, and ſo that hath cauſed ſome obſtruction in the Publication hereof: for ſome were written long ſince, and ſtill did reſt on the Spirits of many to Write, which at firſt was not expected by us; and now at length is made Publick, not to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect on others for what is paſt (if poſſibly it could be avoided) but to clear our Conſciences in the Sight of God, and for the true Information of the Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right in Heart, who do love the Truth more than a bare Notion of it, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not at all times either Saile with the Wind, nor Swim with the Tide; but keep in mind that good Advice (<hi>Viz.) To try all things</hi> (with the Truth) <hi>and hold faſt that which is Good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But for a further <hi>Anſwer</hi> to the <hi>Objection</hi> aforeſaid, We judge it is in vain for any to expect, that the moſt moderate Teſtimony that can be given, on behalf of him, ſhould eſcape without the ſevere Cenſures or Calumniations of ſome of his Oppoſers; becauſe we have often found by Experience, that ſome of his Oppoſers have at ſome times been ſo filled with Prejudice againſt him, that they could hardly with Patience endure to hear him well ſpoken of, and account the Party ſo ſpeaking in his Commendation; to be either a Leavened or Bad Spirit: and therefore we cannot, in our preſent apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, expect, but that his Oppoſers will endeavour to invalidate our Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony: which if they do in publick, it may bring a Concern upon ſome of us, to be more particular and plain (if occaſion be given for it) as to nam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſome particular Perſons, than now we are free to do on this Occaſion; although (as we ſaid before) for any to think, that a Teſtimony for him can be given, and not in ſome ſort to reflect on ſome of his Oppoſers Actions, or Doctrines, it is in vain for any ſo to ſuppoſe. But this we may aſſure the tender Reader, that we have been as ſparing as with clearneſs of Conſcience we could; and if any are offended at us for this plain and honeſt Teſtimony for the Truth, and concerning our Deceaſed Friend: Let all ſuch know that we do account it more true Wiſdom, and better for us to endeavour to pleaſe the Almighty and unchangeable God, than to endeavour to pleaſe Corrupt and Changeable Men, whoſe Breath is in their Noſtrils, and who muſt go from hence and be no more ſeen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="testimony">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:101079:8"/>
               <head>The Teſtimony of <hi>J. J. John Fry, Thomas Crabb,</hi> Sen. <hi>John Sealy, William Colman, John Rogers, Benjamin Laurence.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF the holy Antients in the Days of old did mourn and Iament at the Death of their natural Friends and Relations, or becauſe of the want of them, whoſe Company, Counſel, and good Advice, Labour and Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip they had formerly enjoyed, unto their Edification and Benefit: why ſhould it be thought any way unbeſeeming Chriſtianity or the People of God now, to mourn and take up a great and ſolemn Lamentation for the Loſs (or taking away) of Dear <hi>John Story,</hi> who was very ſerviceable, and his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany pleaſant, and his Advice very good unto us: Did not <hi>Abraham</hi> mourn for <hi>Sarah</hi> his Wife, and <hi>Joſeph</hi> and his Brethren for <hi>Jacob</hi> their Father. And it is Recorded in the Scriptures, 1 <hi>Sam. 25. 1. That</hi> Samuel <hi>Dyed, and all the</hi> Iſraelites <hi>were gathered together, and Lamented for him.</hi> And hath it not run like a natural Stream through all Ages, for People that have true na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Affections to Lament the Loſs of their Friends, and more eſpecially for worthy men of their time, who had been very helpfull and ſerviceable unto them? Therefore, why may not the Friends of <hi>John Story</hi> Lament for him? Seeing there are many yet living who do indeed know that he was a good In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument in the Lords hand, for their Good, demonſtrating the Way of Life unto them; and others can teſtifie that he was very helpfull unto them in his Miniſtry, and by his good Advice and Counſel towards the confirming them in the Truth, in which they had believed.</p>
               <p>And if any ſhould enquire of us, <hi>Why we do Lament for him who was ſo much vilified, and in his latter Days ſo much diſeſteemed by ſome who formerly were then accounted his Friends, and perhaps would then have ſaid (if they had been askt) that he was alſo an Inſtrument of Good unto them in the Lords Hand?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer.</hi> We do not thus Lament for him becauſe we are ſenſible of any Evil he hath done unto any of thoſe who have of late ſo much diſeſteemed, viliſied and rejected him and his Teſtimony; neither becauſe we are ſenſible of any Sin or Treſpaſs that he hath now of late (or indeed, ever in his Life, that we know of, more than what hath commonly or in general happened unto all men; <hi>foraſmuch as all have ſinned, and fall'n ſhort of the Glory of God</hi>) committed againſt God, his Truth, or People, whereby the Lord ſhould be diſpleaſed, and take him away in his Wrath and Diſpleaſure; nay, we do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed believe (having good ground for what we ſay) that he was a Man
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101079:9"/> greatly beloved of God, who endued him with a large Portion of Divine and Heavenly Wiſdom beyond many of his Fellow Servants, and do not in the leaſt doubt of his everlaſting Well-being; but do indeed believe that his Immortal Soul is entred into that Kingdom of Peace and Glory which ſhall never end; becauſe we are inwardly perſwaded, that he walked in his <hi>Day</hi> and <hi>Time,</hi> in that <hi>Strait and Narrow Way which leadeth thereunto;</hi> and that he did honeſtly Serve the Moſt High God with an upright Heart, according to that degree of Grace and Divine Underſtanding that was given unto him to profit withal. So that we do not Lament for him as a People without hope, or doubting of his Reſt and endleſs Peace and Joy in Gods <hi>Kingdom:</hi> But the cauſe of this our Lamentation; is, becauſe that by his removal, or being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away from <hi>amongſt Men,</hi> we are thereby <hi>deprived of the Enjoyment of his good Company,</hi> who hath been unto ſome of us, both like a <hi>Loving Father,</hi> or an <hi>Elder Brother in Chriſt,</hi> and as a <hi>Wiſe Counſelour</hi> unto others. And we can truly ſay, <hi>That his Converſation amongſt us, was ſuch as did well become a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the Goſpel, both in Doctrine and in Practice; for his Doctrine was Sound, and his Converſation Honeſt.</hi> Oh! how wiſe and prudent was his Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour and Carriage amongſt his Friends, and others where he came? How <hi>Grave</hi> and <hi>Solid</hi> would he be in all weighty Matters or Diſcourſe, and yet at ſome other times modeſtly pleaſant among his Friends: and how Devout and Zealous in his Supplications unto the Moſt High, and in his Declaration amongſt Gods People; So that we have Cauſe to Lament for him, as for the Loſs of an able Preacher of Gods Truth: and although we might grant, that ſome others might be more Eloquent and taking with the Affectionate Part in ſome Weak Hearers, by their Declaration, yet we know of none more ſound in Doctrine, nor more Innocent and Blameleſs in their Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, than <hi>J. S.</hi> and his Faithful Companion <hi>J. W.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if any ſhould <hi>Object</hi> againſt what is ſaid of <hi>J. S.</hi> his Zeal, becauſe he did not of late Years Travel ſo much, or keep ſo many Meetings as ſome others may; to that we ſay, That we do believe that there were but very few, who were truly ſenſible of his great Weakneſs and Indiſpoſition of Body that he was afflicted withal for many years, inſomuch that when he did Declare ſomething largely in a Meeting, he was moſt times very ſick at night; or ſometimes very ill two or three Days after: but conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his weakneſs of Body, it is admirable unto us how he hath been carryed forth in his Service in Meetings, time after time, beyond the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of many.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>2dly.</hi> We may Lament for him, as for the loſs of one who had a great gift, both to diſcern, and Detect Eronious Doctrines and practices: and in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending the Doctrines of Truth that he or his fellow Miniſters held forth; if at any time the Prieſts or Profeſſors did oppoſe the ſame: Oh! how did the Ancient Friends praiſe him in that reſpect, and account him as one of the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thys of Gods <hi>Iſrael:</hi> he was a good Pattern and Example in Life and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101079:9"/> amongſt men, for how blamleſs and innocent was it, in great Wiſdom and prudence amongſt the families where he came, giving good advice and counſel, at ſeaſonable opportunities to Parents and Children and Servants for he had a good underſtanding in the things of God, and well experienced in the way of Life, and knew how to ſpeak a word in ſeaſon unto the weak, or ſuch as through an inward exerciſe were, through the enimies Tempatations and Affaults, ready to faint in their minds and turn out of the way; we do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve he had great skill to inform ſuch that were ready to diſpair, and that he was endued with an excellent gift of Wiſdom, and had of the deep things of God, and Miſtries of Life opened unto him, ſo that although his Doctrine was generally ſound and weighty, plain and eaſie to be underſtood by mean ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities yet ſome of us do believe, that he was more ſound and knowing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly in the things of God then ſome by his outward Declaration might eſteem him to be; and through that gift and wiſdom that was beſtowed upon him he knew how to behave himſelf aright in the Aſſemblies of Gods Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and amongſt his fellow ſervants, and could give very good counſel and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice unto ſuch as were but young in the work and ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vice of the Miniſtry: but indeed in this reſpect he had not that opportunity to manifeſt very much of that gift of Wiſdom that God had endued him with, becauſe too many of late years did to much Diſeſteem, Slight and Reject his Counſel and good Adviſe: for he was a true honeſt-man, and ſo was his Converſation among men even from his young years unto his latter end; nor ever was, as we could underſtand, addicted to any <hi>Vice</hi> from his Child-hood unto his dying day, neither was he ſubject to Flatter or Deſſemble with any for his own ends; But we believe that he abhored deceit and flattery from the bottom of his heart: and Doubtleſs he did not any way deſerve thoſe vilyfying terms of a <hi>Dark or Creeping Spirit,</hi> for we never knew him to creep after, or diſſemble with any for his own ſelf-Intreſt, neither did he ever, that we know off, by flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery ſeek after the favour of any Great or Rich Men, that ſo he might gain thereby: but as a true Miniſter of Chriſt, and an able Preacher of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, that ſought not after his own profit or applauſe, Coveting no mans Silver nor Gold, but the real Good, Benefit and Wellfare of Souls: And as he had freely received a Diſpenſation of the Goſpel from the Lord, ſo did he freely Miniſter of it unto others, as the Lord did order him, being (as we ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) an able and ſound Preacher, dividing the Word aright, and was very Intelligible and plain unto mean Capacities, Demonſtrating the way of Life, and exhorting all to walk therein: and we believe that he did not in the leaſt preach for filthy Lucres ſake, but of a ready and willing mind, according to the requirings of Gods holy and bleſſed Spirit; yea doubtleſs in this reſpect he might ſurley have ſaid as <hi>Samuel</hi> did, whoſe <hi>Ox</hi> or <hi>Aſs</hi> did he take, or whoſe <hi>Gold</hi> or <hi>Silver,</hi> or Riches, or Land did he ſeek or covet after.</p>
               <p>He was a good Paſtor, who had a tender regard and care of the Flock of God, where the Lord did order his ſervice, and eſpecially among ſuch where he
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101079:10"/> had laboured much in gathering and confirming of them, his care was great that they might be truly Inſtructed in the way of Life and gathered unto the gift, and grace, of God in themſelves, and that in it all might waite upon God to recevie a Divine and Heavenly underſtanding, and come to be truly Centered and Eſtabliſhed upon the Rock of Ages and in the Truth and way of God.</p>
               <p>And it was his Care and Labour that none might walk diſorderly unto the diſhonour of God, but that ſuch might be Reproved, Adviſed and Admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as Friends did either feel Drawings in themſelves ſo to do, or as there was a ſeaſonable Opportunity wherein Friends might do it in love and tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in a more general way, as they ſaw it their places, that if poſſible, none might go aſtray.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe on the other hand, it was his care that Friends might not be Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed on, or over much driven into the Ceremonial part of Religion, having an Underſtanding given him, to diſcern how apt People have been to be led, and to run into Imitations, and the practice of Outward Things, which ſome others have practiſed, and ſo by that means have not taken that regard unto their own meaſures of the Spirit of God in themſelves, as they ought to have done: But have (through a kind of Zealous Miſtake) ſometimes cryed up and eſteemed the Traditions and Inventions of Men as Ordinances of God, and ſuch have been very forward in Judging and Condemning of others who were of a better Underſtanding, and did ſee further than them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
               <p>And foraſmuch as our dear Friend <hi>J. S.</hi> was, by ſome who profeſs the Truth, miſrepreſented unto many Friends (that did not know him) as a Perſon that was againſt good Order in the Church; and as if he was a Man of a Looſe and Libertine Spirit, or that he did countenance others in their Failings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It is with us to teſtifie, that as it was our Lot to be well acquainted with him (as any in theſe parts, to our Knowledge were) for many years, yet we did never know him to oppoſe any good Order, which any of Gods People did believe was their Duty to perform, either Male or Female, becauſe Gods People are, and ought to be a free and willing Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and what they do, as unto God, it ought to be from a willing Mind, and not by Man's Conſtraint; (<hi>Mark</hi>) it was againſt the Impoſing of it, and ſo not againſt any good Order in it ſelf, which Friends might be in the practice of; for we do know that he did love to ſee good Order among Friends, and that things might be done decently; but he was not for laying the Streſs of Salvation upon any Outward Things or Methods that were, or might be practiced among Gods People; for that would be an Idolizing of it, and Hippocrites may come into an Outward Conformity or Uniformity with Outward Orders or Methods, when they are neither Heirs of Salvation, nor Members of that Church which is in God, of which Jeſus Chriſt is Head:
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101079:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> for he would ſay, <hi>That it was an incumbant Duty on Chriſtians to be Charitable to the Poor, and to relieve their Neceſſities.</hi> But after what Manner or Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod they did extend their Charity, ſo that the end was anſwered, he thought it indifferent.</p>
               <p>For we read in Hiſtory, the Church at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> did Collect every <hi>Firſt Day,</hi> or once a <hi>Week,</hi> but the Church of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> once a <hi>Month,</hi> and doubtleſs they did not fall out or differ about their Method while they ſtood in Gods Counſel. And as to Liberty: that as he did abhor taking any Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in Unrighteouſneſs; ſo on the other hand, he was one that did ſtand much for that Chriſtian Liberty which is in Chriſt Jeſus, and he did both ſpend, and was ſpent for the Goſpel, of the Kingdom, which doth not conſiſt in the ſtrict Obſervance of any Outward Obſervations, or Traditions, or Inventions of Men, but to wait upon God, and ſerve him according to the Manifeſtation of his own Spirit, that he hath given to Man to profit withal, and then, <hi>If the Truth doth make us free, are we free indeed;</hi> we ſay it was this <hi>Chriſtian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Liberty,</hi> that ſtands in Truth and Righteouſneſs, that <hi>J. S.</hi> did ſtand for (and ſo do we) and that all may know the Spirit of Truth to be their Leader in the Things that they do and perform as unto God, that ſo none may act in thoſe things from anothers Meaſure, but from the meaſure of Gods Grace in themſelves, without being Judged one, of, or by another about their Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Liberty and Freedom in the Truth.</p>
               <p>And further we have to ſay for our Deceaſed Friend <hi>J. S.</hi> that he was one whom the Lord had endued with many Spiritual Gifts and pretious Chriſtian Vertues, which were as ſo many Ornaments unto him: and if any ſhould ask what thoſe Gifts and Vertues were, and how, and which way they did appear, and might be demonſtrated to be in him? To this we may an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> His Moderation and Temperance did much appear in the many De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates and Diſcourſes had with him about Religious Matters, wherein he did uſually carry himſelf very moderate, when reaſoning about the Things of God, and as to his Temperance, it did much appear in his Life and Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> He was endued with the Gift and Vertue of Patlence, which did much appear in him, by his patient bearing of thoſe ſevere and bitter Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Oppoſitions that of late years he met withal, as alſo with many falſe and untrue Reports of him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Alſo he did very patiently bear that great and long Weakneſs and Infirmity of Body, that he was very much attended withal, and afflicted with very ſore and grievous Pains, as well as weakneſs in Body, which he underwent with much Patience and Content.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> He had an excellent Gift of <hi>Christian Fortitude</hi> and Conſtancy in his Teſtimony, ſo that notwithſtanding he met with very much Oppoſition,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:101079:11"/> and ſometimes with flattering Perſwaſions, yet he perſevered in the Way, Work and Teſtimony that God had called him unto; and in this reſpect it may in ſome meaſure be ſaid of him as <hi>Jacob</hi> ſaid of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> Gen. 49. 23, 24. <hi>The Archers have ſorely grieved him, and ſhot at him, and hated him, but his Bow abode in Strength, and the Arms of his Hands were made ſtrong, by the Hands of the Almighty God of</hi> Jacob: <hi>from thence is the Shepherd, the Stone of</hi> Iſrael.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> He was endued with a large portion of Chriſtian Charity, which the Apoſtle reckons as one of the moſt excellent Gifts. And if any ſhould ask how that did appear, or was manifeſt in him? We ſay, it did not only appear in him, in that he was not of a <hi>Raſh</hi> and <hi>Rigid Spirit</hi> towards others that might differ from him in Things Indifferent; but was alſo very Charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble towards ſuch in whom he found any true tenderneſs towards God, and was not apt to Judge ſo harſhly and Cenſoriouſly of ſuch, as ſome have been too apt to do, but was willing to inform the underſtanding, when under miſtake, and alſo to perſwade them that oppoſed themſelves, to imbrace the Truth. If we conſider the Fruit of true Charity, ſpoken of by the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. we may indeed ſay, that Charity did largely manifeſt it ſelf in him, becauſe it brought forth, or did manifeſt the ſame Fruits and Effects in and through him as is there ſpoken of by the Apoſtle.</p>
               <p>And as theſe and other <hi>Chriſtian Vertues</hi> did appear and were manifeſted in him while he was amongſt us; ſo we are credibly informed by ſome Friends of <hi>Weſtmoreland</hi> (that were with him in the time of his laſt Sickneſs) that he gave very good Counſel and Advice to Friends that were with him, and that he being very weak in Body, but not in much pain, as was ſuppoſed by thoſe who were about him, he very gently breath'd his laſt, and laid down his Head in much Peace and Quietneſs of Mind and Spirit.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Given forth at <hi>Sutton</hi> on <date>the <hi>1ſt.</hi> Day of the <hi>11th.</hi> Month 1682.</date>
                  </dateline> and
<signed>Subſcribed by us, on the behalf of our ſelves and many more Friends of <hi>Wiltſhire,</hi> that are concerned and conſented un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Publiſhing hereof.
<list>
                        <item>John Jennings.</item>
                        <item>John Fry.</item>
                        <item>Thomas Crabb, <hi>Sen.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>John Sealy.</item>
                        <item>William Colman.</item>
                        <item>John Rogers.</item>
                        <item>Benjamin Lawrance.</item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="testimony">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:101079:11"/>
               <head>The Teſtimony of <hi>John Metrevers.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Short Teſtimony Concerning <hi>John Story,</hi> that worthy Servant of the Living God, though dead, yet the Seal of his Miniſtry and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice for God in his Day and Age, lives in the Remembrance, and hath an Impreſſion on the Hearts of many in theſe Parts: and foraſmuch as the Unchangeable Truth remains the ſame as ever; we cannot forget thoſe worthy Meſſengers, who in the Days of our young and tender Years came amongſt us in the Demonſtration of the Spirit and Power of Almighty God, not only to proclaim a Day of Vengence from God upon that Part or Nature in Man that hath tranſgreſſed his Law, but alſo with a Meſſage of Peace and Glad-tidings unto our Souls. And now as for my Dear Friend <hi>John Story</hi> in particular, concerning whom I have a few words, which at this time reſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my Spirit, to treat about. I have this to ſay, and that not by here-ſay, or to boaſt in another Mans Words, but according to that true and Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Knowledge which I have had of him for theſe ſeven or eight and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years paſt, it being about the Year 1654, or 1655 (as near as I can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member) that this worthy Servant of the Almighty God came amongſt us (into <hi>Wiltſhire</hi>) at which time for my own part, I was about fourteen years of Age, notwithſtanding which, what ſhall I ſay, it is even with me at this time to ſignifie, That had I the Tongue of an <hi>Orator,</hi> or the Pen of a <hi>Ready</hi> Writer, I could not demonſtrate the Senſe that now lives and remains upon my Spirit, of the Mighty Power of God that appeared in, and through that Man, both in Life and Doctrine, whereby I was at that time (though but young in years) often ſweetly Refreſhed and Comforted in his Company, by that Eternal Power that dwelt with and ran through him. Oh! What ſhall I ſay, my Heart at this time is even melted in the Conſideration thereof: his Meſſage then was, to direct all to turn inward from the <hi>Lo here,</hi> and the <hi>Lo there,</hi> to the Grace, Light, or Spirit within, which according to Meaſure, was given to all, aſſuring all unto whom he gave the Word of Exhortation, that it being obeyed and followed in all its Requirings, was that only means, and that in which the ſufficiency for Salvation of the Soul conſiſted; this Doctrine was received by many, by the Mighty Power of God, which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companyed and manifeſted it ſelf through that Man, many brought to the Faith; and ſo as the Lord made way, he travelled from Place to Place, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing Meetings up and down among Friends, directing all as above menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, and unfolding the Scriptures by way of <hi>Parables,</hi> and opening to the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:101079:12"/> Edification of the Hearer, many hard Sayings, both to the Convincing of thoſe that receiv'd it, and Admiration of many that receiv'd it not, inſomuch that my Ears have heard it acknowledged and confeſſed unto, that the Doctrine ſo Preach't through the Power and Demonſtration of the Spirit, as then it was, would never fail while the Water keeps its Courſe; his Work was alſo very much among the <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Profeſſors</hi> of that Age, who then like <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gog,</hi> joyned together againſt the Lord and his <hi>Anointed:</hi> but the Lords Power and Preſence being with him, and always giving of him both Mouth and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, he was thereby furniſhed to ſpeak a word in due ſeaſon, both to the <hi>Strengthening and Comforting the Weak and Feeble of the Flock,</hi> whom he had Laboured and Travelled for; and alſo to the ſtopping the Mouths of all <hi>Gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayers,</hi> whoſe Oppoſition at that day was very great. Much could I ſpeak, and that within the compaſs of my own knowledge, to the particulars of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Sufferings by way of Impriſonment, and other <hi>Dangers</hi> and <hi>Jeopardies</hi> that he was often in, in his <hi>Maſters Work and Service,</hi> which I ſhall here omit, and that becauſe I would rather ſtraiten my ſelf than be tedious to the Reader; when that is ſaid, I have this further to add, which I cannot be clear to omit, or paſs by, <hi>Viz. That he was always a very plain hearted Man, in plainneſs ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Truth to the Face, and never could endure, either in himſelf or others, Whiſpering or Backbiting, but would ſharply reprove it whereever he found it; and furthermore all Outward Shews, Formalities, Jeſtures, or Deportments whatſoever, that was by the Creature brought forth in the Likeneſs or Imitation of the true Power, without the Powers bringing forth thereof, his Righteous Soul always ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred:</hi> And for the Confirmation thereof, one thing amongſt many I well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member; that whereas there was a Day of ſhaking the Outward Body by the ſtirrings of the true Power, ſome in imitation thereof, as I have obſerved in his Preſence, in their own Strength have imitated the like, which he would in the Integrity of his Soul Judge, ſaying, <hi>Away with Deceit:</hi> and ſuch like words, exhorting and adviſing all to be plain hearted, and that they ſhould be what they appear'd to be by the Grace of God, and not otherwiſe. And ſo remaining from time to time, as a Man not ſubject to change his way, holding forth his Teſtimony in Faithfulneſs to God, not only againſt prophane and ſinful Actions, but alſo againſt all Formalities ſet up by Man, though under pretence of the Motion of the true Power, adviſing the Creature to be inward to God, and there to wait, to know the true Power it ſelf to bring forth a Form through every man, whereby they might have the certain Senſe and Knowledge how to do and perform the thing well pleaſing to their heavenly Father, that thereby they might in the end be accepted of him; he was not a Man of Shadows, but for the Subſtantial Part of Religion: and to his laſt, I very well remember, his Diſcourſe run much after this manner, <hi>That they were the only Bleſſed People, and for evermore happy, who had received the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the right Spirit, if ſo be they continued to wait and walk therein to the end of their Days, becauſe it is they that remain in well doing unto the end that
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:101079:12"/> ſhall be Crowned.</hi> Unto which End it is my Faith and Belief in God, he hath attained, and is now entred into the Joys of that Heavenly Kingdom, out of the reach of all envious and clamorous Tongues, where the wicked ceaſe from troubling, and the weary be at reſt, there the Priſoners reſt together, they hear not the voice of the Oppreſſor, the Small and great are there, and the Servant is free from his Maſter.</p>
               <p>And he having been ſerviceable in the Hand of the Lord, and Inſtrumental to Convert many Souls to God, doth, and muſt ſhine as a Star in the Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God. So having eaſed my Mind by writing theſe few Lines before expreſt, concerning this my dear Friend, of whom, I do aſſure the Reader, I had as certain a knowledge, as the very import of the words will bear: and foraſmuch as the <hi>Harveſt</hi> yet remains great, and the true Labourers therein are but few, what further ſhall I ſay, but with this to conclude, <hi>Viz. Let us cry mightily to the great Lord of the Harveſt to pour forth a double portion of his Spirit upon ſome worthy Inſtrument, as he did upon</hi> Eliſha, <hi>to Succeed him in that Work and Service.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>J. M.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="testimony">
               <head>The Teſtimony of <hi>Robert Arch.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FRiends, unto all you do I write, who have in any meaſure ſecretly or openly vilifyed and reproached that Servant of the Lord, <hi>J. S.</hi> or have had any hand in the hindring of him in his bearing a faithful Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to the Truth, of which he was an Able Miniſter, in publiſhing the Goſpel of Chriſt, and have endeavoured to the utmoſt of your Power, to ſtop and hinder him in his Declaration and Travel amongſt the People of God, by evil Surmiſings and falſe Reports and Accuſations, have raiſed a Prejudice in the Hearts of People againſt him, without any juſt Cauſe on his part given, that I know of. Conſider, O Friends, What is the Cauſe that ye have ſo done? Have ye known him to be a Man of an ill Life, or a bad Converſation? Or hath he committed any Evil, or Sinned or Tranſgreſſed againſt God, his Truth or People, that ye have ſo hated him? Or hath he been one that hath Preached any Falſe Doctrine, or held any Principles contrary to Truth? Or did he bring in any <hi>Innovations</hi> amongſt the People of God, or build again any of thoſe things that he hath by his Miniſtry deſtroyed in others? If he hath done none of thoſe things, nor committed any Perſonal Treſpaſs againſt you, as ſome of you have confeſſed, what then was the cauſe of your Envy and hating of him? Was it becauſe he would not bow down, nor Worſhip any
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:101079:13"/> other God than the <hi>God of Iſrael?</hi> Or was it becauſe he would not ſubmit to ſome <hi>Outward Orders, Preſcriptions,</hi> or <hi>Rules</hi> preſcribed by Fall'n Man? If this be the Cauſe, then do not you Condemn your ſelves in Judging of him? For what People in this latter Age have laboured and Travelled more than ſome of you have done, to bring People out of the Practice and Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of <hi>Outward Things,</hi> which they called, <hi>The Ordinances of Chriſt,</hi> ſome of which the Saints in Times paſt did Practice, and perform for a Time, as the Scripture maketh mention, and alſo from the many <hi>Forms, Decrees</hi> and <hi>Orders</hi> that the Profeſſors have been jangling about, and Perſecuting one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, counting it all but Dung and Droſs in compariſon of the Grace of God, or Light of Chriſt, which was held forth to be ſufficient to lead unto Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and in the Light we were directed to wait upon God to know his Mind and Will, to act and do in <hi>Outward Things</hi> as God ſhould direct us by his Good Spirit. And have you not look't upon all thoſe <hi>Outward Orders, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions</hi> and <hi>Ordinances,</hi> as the <hi>Outward Court of the Temple</hi> that was given unto the Gentiles to tread under Foot: and yet now after all theſe large De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations and Teſtimonies againſt thoſe <hi>Outward Things,</hi> for you to incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage the Setting up ſuch Things; and not only ſo, but to Judge and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn others for not Conforming unto your <hi>Outward Orders,</hi> Cenſuring Friends out of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> that do not practice them, which is the greateſt Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty that you can inflict, for want of Outward Power: as if the Saints Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſtood in the Practice and Performance of thoſe <hi>Outward Orders.</hi> Oh! Friends, conſider of theſe Things, and lay it to heart; <hi>for this is not doing as you would have others do unto you:</hi> and do not think that the Saints Unity ſtands in thoſe Things, but in the Spirit and Truth. Therefore Friends, I do exhort and admoniſh you all to repent of the Evil you have done againſt the aboveſaid Servant of the Lord <hi>J. S.</hi> or againſt any other of his Faithful Friends and Brethren; and beware in time to come, and watch in the Light of the Son of God againſt that Spirit in you that Luſts to Envy, or to Hate, Oppoſe or Perſecute your Brethren: And remember what the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> ſaid, <hi>He that ſaith he is in the Light, and hateth his Brother, is in Darkneſs, and walketh in Darkneſs, and knoweth not whether he goeth, becauſe the Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs hath blinded his Eyes.</hi> So let this be a Warning unto you all, that you may not in time to come ſtop or hinder any of the the Servants of the Lord in the Work of the Miniſtry, that ſo you may avoid that Sentence of, <hi>Go ye Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed:</hi> and which will be the Portion of all thoſe that are found ſmiting their Fellow Servants.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>R. A.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="testimony">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:101079:13"/>
               <head>Leonard Coal's Teſtimony.</head>
               <p>DEar <hi>John Story,</hi> whom the Lord made an Inſtrument in his Hand, and fil'd with Heavenly Treaſure, and gave him his Word to Declare, which he often did, in the Counſel and Wiſdom received of God, diſpenſing it aright to the Capacities and Underſtandings of the Hearers, for the opening thereof, and did reach to Gods Witneſs in many: he was well known to me, and I had (through the Goodneſs of the Lord) opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to accompany him of late in ſome of his Travels; in which time, and ever ſince I knew him, which was about twenty years, he always behav'd himſelf as a Pattern of Righteouſneſs, which anſwered the Good in all.</p>
               <p>He was always ready to give Advice to the Weak, and Inſtruction to thoſe who were enquiring the Way to Gods Kingdom, and through the Operation of Gods Spirit, could direct them to diſtinguiſh between the Im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ginacions of the Enemies deceitful working, and Imaginations of their own Hearts, and the true Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ions of Gods Spirit: which Motion I am fully perſwaded, he knew right well, he much deſired and prayed for Quietneſs and Unity in the One Spirit of God, and that all Friends might know it, and follow the Lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and Guidance of it in all things that relate to Gods Worſhip and Service, and that they might not act by Imitation on that account: and that People might come to know the way to Gods Kingdom, and walk in it: he often de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired God to forgive thoſe that ſpoke evil of him, and that they might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of their Slanderous and Lying Reports, and Falſe Propheſies of him. And now the Lord hath taken him to himſelf, out of the reach of them all: he is gone to his Reſt, where no Sorrow nor Tears are, I am fully perſwaded: And it is my earneſt Deſire, that the Lord would be pleaſed to raiſe up more ſuch Inſtruments for his own Work and Service, as it pleaſeth him.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>L. C.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="testimony">
               <head>Benjamin Coal's Teſtimony.</head>
               <p>SInce I heard of the Deceaſe of dear <hi>John Story,</hi> there hath been a Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony in my Heart to give forth concerning him, whom I dearly loved for the Truths ſake, in which I have been often Comforted and truly Refreſhed through him: It is now towards twenty years ſince I came acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:101079:14"/> with him; and our long Impriſonment in the heat of Perſecution of <hi>Friends</hi> in <hi>Reading,</hi> he came ſeveral times to Viſit us in Priſon, and many pretious opportunities we had with him in Priſon, and were thereby wuch comforted and ſtrengthened in our Suffering condition, and many Hearts were tendered and ſweetly conſolated, at that time, in a real ſenſe of the living preſence of the Lord God, which was with us; and ſome that came into the Priſon were Convinced of the Truth; ſince which he hath often Viſited us in our Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; alſo I have from time to time been in his company, both in Publick and Private, and taken many ſerious Obſervations of his Deportment, which hath been Grave and as a Servant of Chriſt; yea, it was ſuch, that from the firſt to to the laſt time I ſaw him (which was not many Months ſince) I never had acquaintance with any that exceeded him in a good Life and Converſation: And the Lord endued him with a Gift beyond many in declaring the Truth, and many were Convinced and turned to God by him; He had a divine Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding given him, to divide the Word aright, he was able and ready to inform Peoples Underſtandings, to give Counſel and good Advice to <hi>Sion's Travellors,</hi> who were at any time in a bewildred condition, whereby many were often relieved and comforted, that have been in trouble under the temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of the Enemy of mans Peace. He was of a loving kind Temper to all, and his Company was very comfortable to me, when Trials and Sufferings have attended <hi>Friends,</hi> upon any account, for a Teſtimony to the Truth, he hath been an Encourager and Strengthener to many therein: and I never knew him to ſpeak ſlightingly, or account it an Indifferent thing to be faithful to God in that reſpect, or in any other good Work and Service, wherein we might ſerve the Lord and one another; but frequently exhorted and counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Friends,</hi> to be Zealous and Dilligent in wairing upon the Lord to know and anſwer his Requirings, both by Doing, Suffering, and bearing Teſtimony for his Name and Truth upon Earth, that ſo they might Honour the Lord, and come to reſt in Peace for ever.</p>
               <p>And notwithſtanding he met with many Exerciſes and Troubles among men, yet the Lord was pleaſed to give him much Patience, and when he hath been grieved and abuſed by any, he manifeſted much of a Spirit of Forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Longſuffering towards his Oppoſers, not rendring Even for Evil.</p>
               <p>I have often heard him ſpeak much in Commendation of many Antient Brethren which are Deceaſed, whom the Lord raiſed up to Preach and Publiſh the Everlaſting Goſpel in the beginning, and how pretious and acceptable the Viſitation of the Lord was to many that were in Diſtreſs and Mourned in ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Places, for want of the <hi>Saving Knowledge of God,</hi> which is Life to the Soul.</p>
               <p>And in a godly Care for the Honour and Propagation of Truth, and the good of Soules, I know he was often very deeply concerned and bowed in Spirit; and was a man of Sorrows, often with much fervent Zeal praying for the Proſperity of the Lords Work, and that all that which was of a hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:101079:14"/> nature might be utterly deſtroyed from among the Lords People, and that Love unfeigned with the increaſe of Righteouſneſs, which brings everlaſting Peace might abound amongſt us; For this was his ſoul often in ſupplication and Prayers unto the Lord God, both in Publick and Private amongſt <hi>Friends.</hi> Oh! What ſhall I ſay, for my heart is filled at this time, and often tendred in the remembrance of the Lords Love, and thoſe ſweet and ſeaſonable Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities which I have had with this my dear Friend, in which I have often admired the goodneſs of God, who afforded us ſuch good Opportunities wherein my heart hath many times been overcome and rejoyced, in a ſenſe of the feeling of the diſſolving and tendering Power and living Preſence of the Lord God, who aſſiſted him with his heavenly wiſdom and ſtrength, and the teſtimony of Truth often opened through him, reaching and extending unto many ſtates and conditions, even as the ſtill Sowres that deſcended upon the tender Graſs in its due ſeaſon; for which my Soul hath bleſſed the Lord on his behalf many a ſeaſon, and which was and is the only ground and cauſe of my Love to him and all the Lords faithful Servants, whom I cannot but truly eſteem for the Truths ſake, and account worthy of double Honour; and I have often thought, that if we ſhould not truly love and eſteem of ſuch in the Truth, it might be juſt with the Lord to let us know the want of them, and to Suffer a Famine of the Word and a Cloud of Ignorance and Darkneſs again to overſpread the Earth, which I deſire the Lord may in his Mercy prevent, and that more faithful Inſtruments and living Witneſſes for his bleſſed Name and Truth, in the room and ſtead of them that are gone to their Reſt, may yet be raiſed up, and that many may yet be gathered unto God, for the Comfort and Encouragement of the Lords People, in this Age and the Ages to come.</p>
               <p>Much more I might ſay concerning this faithful Servant of God, according to my knowledge, but herein I have ſatisfaction, believing he is now at Reſt, and out of all his Troubles and Exerciſes which in this world he had his ſhare of, and through Death hath obtained a Crown and Kingdom that is Everlaſting, where all Tears are wiped away, and Sorrow and Sighing comes to an End.</p>
               <p>Oh that we who are left behind may not content our ſelves that this our dear <hi>Friend</hi> live well, and is entered into everlaſting felicity, but may follow the Example of this and all the reſt of our dear <hi>Brethren</hi> which are gon before, in all faithfulneſs and circumſpect walking, ſerving the Lord in ſincerity and holy Converſation, keeping to the Word of his Grace and Truth, through which we may overcome all Corruptions, receive and poſſeſs the Recompence of endleſs Peace, Joy and Happineſs when time in this fading World comes to an end; that God over all may be glorified, who alone is worthy to be Feared and Praiſed for ever and evermore.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>B. C.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Reading,</hi> 
                     <date>the <hi>15th.</hi> of the <hi>10th.</hi> Month, 8681.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="testimony">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:101079:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>Leonard Keep's <hi>Teſtimony.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SInce I heard there would be ſomething Printed concerning our dear <hi>Friend J. S.</hi> it was with me this 15<hi>th.</hi> of the 12<hi>th. Month</hi> 1682, to give in this ſhort Teſtimony concerning him. He was a Man of Peace and inſtrumental in the Hand of the Lord for the turning many to Righteouſneſs: he deſired the good of all People, and I believe is now entered into Reſt and Peace with the Lord, where all Tears will be wiped away, and Longſuffering come to an end, notwithſtanding Blindneſs hath happned to many in this Age, that they could not ſee him to be ſo by reaſon of the Enmity and Prejudice that have entred their minds, more through the Inſtigation I believe of others, than from any deportment that appeared by him. I have been in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany often both in Meetings and out of Meetings, and am an Eye and Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witneſs of what is here writ, I have often heard him put a more favourable Conſtruction upon his Oppoſers actions, than I believe they could put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. I have heard him openly oppoſed and charged falſly, and when he hath called for Proof of what hath been ſaid, there hath nothing been made appear, but at the laſt ſhift have referred <hi>Friends</hi> to the 44 <hi>Articles</hi> of <hi>London. M. C.</hi> may remember this: And I have heard him ſpoke over, when he hath had a concern to the Meeting (and had begun to ſpeak firſt, as many may remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber) which I muſt needs ſay was not practiſed amongſt us in the beginning, nor was it ſo in the Primitive times, for then all might ſpeak one by one, that had any thing upon them as a concern to the People: but theſe things hath happened amongſt us in theſe latter times, ſince ſome have been apt to pin their Faith on other folks Sleeves, and then may ſpeak words as they would have them, or elſe their own, and it hath been ſaid it is the Word of the Lord, when time hath manifeſted it to be otherwiſe. So many are kindling a fire of their own, and warming themſelves by the ſparks thereof, whoſe Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will be ſuch as they had formerly that were ſo doing, unleſs they repent, they muſt lye down in ſorrow. God Almighty, if it be thy will, give to all that have been Oppoſers of him, a ſight of what they have been and are yet a doing, that ſo they may ſay as it was once ſaid, <hi>Let the time past be ſufficient, and that for time to come they may do ſo no more.</hi> And whatever any may think I have nothing but good will to all men.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>L. K.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="testimony">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:101079:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Thomas Curtis</hi>'s Teſtimony, who at ſome time was his Companion in his Travels.</head>
               <p>AS it was ſaid by <hi>David</hi> concerning <hi>Jonathan</hi> after his Death, ſo can I in Truth ſay touching my antient Friend and Brother in the Truth, <hi>John Story: Viz. Very pleaſant haſt thou been unto me;</hi> and dear <hi>John,</hi> although thy Body be turned to the Duſt, yet thy Name liveth now thou art dead, and the memorial of thy Faithfulneſs remains amongſt thy Brethren; thy Portion is with the Righteous, who ſhall be had in Everlaſting Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, and ſhall continue (as an everlaſting Foundation) time ſhall declare the Meekneſs of thy Nature, and that Gentleneſs that was in thee towards the Flock of God; for in the <hi>Lamb-like Nature</hi> didſt thou come amongſt us, and as a <hi>Lamb among Wolves,</hi> ſo was thy Carriage: <hi>Wiſdom</hi> went before thee, and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> was thy Guide: So that when firſt I ſaw thy Face, thou waſt to me a Meſſenger of God, and though thou met with many under va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Forms, oppoſing each other, yet how carefully didſt thou inſtruct them, and with great diligence helped th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir Weakneſs; and ſuch was thy Carriage after a ſweet manner, that I ſoon ſaw a <hi>Door of Hope</hi> opened by the Lord for the Relief of many: and although thou waſt but a Lad, becauſe of thy tender Years, yet ſuch Gravity did appear in thee, as made both <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>Young</hi> to love thee; and thy Teſtimony was not from Man, neither waſt thou ſent by any <hi>Born after the Fleſh,</hi> but thy Teſtimony was from Heaven, and it did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh the Work that the Lord ſent thee for; and thy Doctrine dropt as the <hi>Dew</hi> upon the Tender-hearted: and ſurely the Spirit of the Lord was up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee, and the Meek and Quiet Spirit was in thee, which ever was, and ſtill is of great price with the Lord; and thou didſt Preach the Glad-tyding of Salvation unto many that were far from the Almighty, bearing a Faithful Teſtimony unto Chriſt Jeſus; the true Light, that inwardly enlightens every Man, and to the Word nigh in the Heart and in the Mouth, to the Anointing within, and (unto the univerſality of that Grace which brings Salvation) of its <hi>Appearing</hi> to all Mankind, and to the <hi>Manifeſtation</hi> of the Spirit of Truth that is is given unto all to profit with; labouring to undeceive all, and to bring from the <hi>Outſide Forms, Beggerly Elements, Traditions, Rudiments,</hi> and <hi>Inventions of Men</hi> (wherein many had been kept in Bondage) to Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, the Living Way, the Truth and Life, the true Shepherd and Biſhop of the Soul, in his Light to wait for Counſel and Directions, in all things to be Led, Guided and Governed by him alone, who was, and is the Lawgiver, and unto whom all Power in Heaven and Earth is committed, whoſe Kingdom
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:101079:16"/> is not of this World, who alone hath power over the Conſcience, and over the Inward Man; this is his Glory, which he never did, nor never will give unto another, and in this thou waſt a Faithful <hi>Meſſenger</hi> and <hi>Miniſter,</hi> turning many from Darkneſs to Light, and from the Power of Satan unto God; and ſo taught many the way through Judgment unto Life, that their Hearts did burn within them, whil'ſt in their Hearts they did learn Righteouſneſs, which made many to confeſs, to the Glory of God, <hi>That thou waſt ſent of God, to ſhew the way unto the Reſt that God had prepared for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright Hearted.</hi> And truly ſuch a Power went with thee, that not I alone, but many of the Land came to hear the joyful Sound, and were turned to the true Light, and the God of Heaven was with thee, and a true Ambaſſadour of Chriſt Jeſus waſt thou, beſeeching Men to be reconciled unto the Lord; aſſuring of us, <hi>That God had ſent his Son to Redeem our Souls, by changing of our Natures, and to bleſs us, by turning every one of us from our Evil Doings.</hi> And having a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing Miniſtry committed to thee of God, thou became an Inſtrument in his hand to the opening of our Underſtandings, and to the building us up in the Living Faith, which made us bleſs the Lord for thy coming in his Name; and for the Change that in due time was wrought in us; and God gave us a Witneſs in our own Boſomes, <hi>That thou waſt an Apoſtle of the True and Heavenly Profeſſion, and that thou, by the aſſiſtance of the Power of God accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panying thee, directed our Feet into the Way of Peace.</hi> For which, my Soul, <hi>Praiſe thou the Lord, and all that is within me ſhall bleſs his Name,</hi> with many more, who can ſet to their Seals, that thou waſt an Inſtrument in the hand of God, of their Converſion, and a Man through whom the Way of Life was demonſtrated amongſt us) and many became Witneſſes, <hi>That the Earth was rent aſunder, and the Stout-hearted bowed, and the Strong did fall before thee;</hi> Thou valluedſt neither Riches nor Glory, neither did any of thoſe Things overtake thee; but as an <hi>Armed Man,</hi> and a <hi>Champion</hi> indeed, thy <hi>Warefare</hi> was againſt <hi>Spiritual Wickedneſs,</hi> and thy Travel was, <hi>That the Ax of God might be laid to the Root of the Corrupt Three, that no untimely Fruit might grow amongſt us;</hi> and thou ſought not the Treaſures of the Earth, nor to be great amongſt thy Brethren, but to do the Will of thy Maſter was thy delight, thou waſt a true Traveller in thy Day, and thy Journying was much on foot (ſeveral years) the <hi>Rain</hi> abſtructed thee not in the Morning, neither could the Scorching <hi>Sun</hi> at Noon-day hinder thy Progreſs (for thy Feet were ſhod with the Preparation of the Goſpel) and a true Traveller waſt thou in the Work of the Lord, for thy Bow did abide in its full Strength, and the Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers were made to fall, and the Wicked fled before thee, thou didſt not turn thy Back, but often encounteredſt Gainſayers on many Occaſions, and never waſt worſted, (as ever I could hear) in any of thy Aſſaults; for thou was not only experienced in the Work thou undertook'ſt, but very well read in that excellent Book, the <hi>Holy Scriptures</hi>) and an aptneſs was in thee to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Weakneſs of thy Oppoſers, and having gotten hold of thy Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:101079:16"/> no Flattery could prevail, nor Inchantment pervert thee, until thou made him confeſs unto the Truth, for the God of the whole Earth was with thee, and the Slain of the Lord were many; and ſuch Divine Counſel did at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend thy Habitation, that no Profeſſion was able, in Truth to withſtand thy Teſtimony; and thou waſt plentifully endued with the Spirit of the Lord, whereby thou appearedſt as his <hi>Battle<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Ax,</hi> and the Stroak thereof made the Rocks give way, and the Mountains cleft in funder, inſomuch as the Wiſdom of the Wiſe-men failed them, and the Counſel of the Prudent was not found amongſt them, for their Learning could not hide them, nor the <hi>Logician's</hi> Subtilty could not preſerve them, but over all their Baits thou trampled'ſt, and many times caught them in their own Snare: and all this Conqueſt was not gotten by Outward <hi>Bow</hi> or <hi>Spear,</hi> but by the Spirit of the Living God; and to ſpeak the truth of thee, <hi>It was thy Meat and thy Drink to do the Will of thy Maſter;</hi> thy Care was great in viſiting the Mountains, where many the Sheep of <hi>Gods Paſture,</hi> were ſcattered, and what wreſtling with the Power of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs thou hadſt, to recover the Loſt Sheep of the Houſe of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> the <hi>North</hi> can tell the deep Exerciſes of that Day, and the continual Burthen that was then with thee to viſit the Dark Corners that were full of Cruelty, and what haſte thou made then then to viſit the Steeple-houſe, forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thy ordinary Food, until thy Maſter Chriſt Jeſus his Work was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed. But O the hardſhip that ſometimes thou met with: Were not the <hi>Cudgels</hi> ſometimes laid on about thy Head by Ungodly Men? And did not they in great fury daſh thee in the face with their Clouted Shoes until the Blood hath guſhed out of thy Mouth in a large meaſure? Doubtleſs ſuch like Treatment thou haſt imbraced, that the Oppreſſed might be recovered, and the Priſoner brought out of the horrible Pit, in which there was no Water: and thy Legs did not fail thee in this Travel, becauſe the Lord was with thee, neither did thy Strength depart from thee, becauſe the Bread from Heaven was thy Delight, and often <hi>Honey</hi> out of the Rock did the Lord beſtow on thee: Springs can tell the Joy they often adminiſtred<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the Comfort that they often beſtowed on thee in that Day, when the Bowels of the Earth feemed to be ſhut up, and all other Outward Comforts departed from thee, and this from one Week to another was thy Travel, ſo that the <hi>North</hi> ſounds out thy Praiſe, and the <hi>Weſt</hi> do tell of thee; many in the <hi>South</hi> beſides my ſelf can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but rejoyce in the Lord, and be glad that God prepared our Hearts, and made thee as a ſharp <hi>Inſtrument</hi> in his hand, to daſh all our <hi>Formal Profeſſions</hi> to pieces, that the Broken-hearted might be bound up, and that we might be created anew unto his Glory: and when we come truly to know the Lord, and to help to fill up the Meaſures of the Sufferings of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that was behind for us to fill up, and were Priſoners for Conſcience fake; what Care was upon thee in that Day, that we might be Viſited: And, Oh! the pretious Opportunities and often Viſitations that then thou gave us, Fear did not ſurpriſe thee, nor the Priſon daunt thee, from adminiſtring to us
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:101079:17"/> the Comforts of the Holy Ghoſt, for we were the Priſoners of the Lord, and the wrath of men was turned upon us, but thou comforted'ſt our hearts with this teſtimony (agreable to our one Faith) <hi>that the Wrath of Man would turn to the Praiſe of God,</hi> and <hi>the reſt God would reſtrain:</hi> Thy many Viſitations are not forgotten, although thy Silver Cord be looſed and thy Golden Boule be broken; neither art thou out of our Remembrance, although thou art De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from us, and though many have a great loſs, yet my loſs is far greater, becauſe of my often Journying with thee, being in ſuch my Travels, a pertaker with thee of the Breſts of Conſolation, and of the Milk of the Word of Life: Thou waſt not willing to eat thy Morſel alone, but that others might per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of the ſame Table, and come to the Injoyment of the Feaſt of Fat things and though ſomtimes I have met with hard ſpeeches, and been Rendered as a <hi>dark Spirit,</hi> and gone under many Reproaches, and my wayes endeavoured to be hedged up, (as in <hi>Ireland</hi> and ſome other parts) and called to an account a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout thy deportment, becauſe of matters laid to thy Charge, yet proving them falſe, the Reporters have confeſſed (and to the Glory of the Lord) that thou waſt not the man: But thou art aſcended above the ſtrife of Tongues, and we may come to thee, but thou ſhalt never return to us: yet Days ſhall ſpeak of the loſs of ſuch a Prophet, becauſe, <hi>pretious in the Sight of the Lord is the death of his Saints;</hi> and now in thy latter day when, thou haſt ſpent thy ſtrength in the Service of the Lord, notwithſtanding great weakneſs of Body was upon thee, yet thou planted, a Vineyard, and then eat of the Fruit, thou feedeſt the Flock, and eat of the Milk thereof, at which ſome were angry, and either knew not, or willingly forgot thy former Travels for the Goſpel-ſake, when thou ſpared not thy Fleſh, and ſometimes thy Blood to ſhew them that were diſtreſſed, the way to the Kingdom; yet how evilly have ſome ſpoken of thee, as if thou wert negligent in the Lord's ſervice, when to the utmoſt thou did, what thou waſt able, and when thy Leggs would not perform the ſervice of thy mind, thou then Rode up and down according to thine ability that then was given thee; and we often looked for thy change, many years before thy Departure, but what hard hap had the Prophet to be a Fool, and the Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al man to be mad, to Propheſie in the Name of the Lord, that <hi>thou John Story ſhould that year dye;</hi> when neither did the Lord ſend him, now his Propheſie came to paſs; but the God of Heaven made manifeſt his kindneſs to thee, kept thee alive beyond many of our expectations, and made the fooliſh Prophet to confeſs (as I have been Informed to this purpoſe) that it was an <hi>Imagination of his own brain, &amp; not the Word of the Lord.</hi> And thus his Words became his Burthen in his Life time; and ſeeing he is alſo gone to the Earth, we muſt leave him to the Lord; and this I mentioned the rather, becauſe I was an Eye and Ear Witneſs of the Declaration of that <hi>falſe Propheſie:</hi> But Oh! the weakneſs of Body that then appeared in thee, thou didſt not much controvert with him, but ſaid, <hi>time would ſoon manifeſt it,</hi> thy years being almoſt at an end; and ſo committed the cauſe to God; the Judge of all, for thou waſt no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtriver, neither did Contention
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:101079:17"/> dwell with thee in that matter, but in much Patience thou heardſt his words: and as thy Beginning was, ſo was thy End, in the Lamb's War, with the Lamb's Nature: thou wenteſt from the <hi>South</hi> to the <hi>Weſt,</hi> taking thy leave of thy Friends, and then returned into the <hi>North;</hi> where, in the weakneſs of Body thou viſitedſt the People of the Lord, and having compleated thy Maſters Buſineſs, thou encounteredſt with Death, and overcame it, and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly yielded up thy ſelf into the Arms of the Almighty, left the World, and art gone unto God, where, out of the reach of all thy Adverſaries thou art, in that Manſion that Jeſus Chriſt hath prepared for his People, where no De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyer ſhall ever come.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>T. C.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <head>An ELEGY of <hi>John Story</hi> by <hi>John Raunce.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IN Peace with God he now is gone to Reſt,</l>
                  <l>Out of this World, in which he was Oppreſt.</l>
                  <l>Having ill <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſage met from his Brethren:</l>
                  <l>Nothing would do with ſome, like wilful Men</l>
                  <l>So ſet themſelves, that they would not believe</l>
                  <l>That he ſpoke Truth, this did him ſorely grive;</l>
                  <l>Oppreſſing Sorrows did his Body pine,</l>
                  <l>Rending his Soul with Grief from time to time;</l>
                  <l>Yet in all this the Lord he always found;</l>
                  <l>Yea Help from God did ſtill to him abound;</l>
                  <l>Yea and Amen his Grace to him was Free</l>
                  <l>Yea to the End his Grace hath Saved thee;</l>
                  <l>Yea now he doth poſſeſs <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yea now Chriſt is his only <hi>Requiem.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="remembrance">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:101079:18"/>
               <head>More in Remembrance of <hi>John Story.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THy Lot was like Good Prophets gone before,</l>
                  <l>With Lamb like Nature thou as they did bear</l>
                  <l>The frowns of Friends and Enemies much more,</l>
                  <l>Whil'ſt Envy did of thee ſore things declare:</l>
                  <l>Oh happy thou, who didſt with Meekneſs then</l>
                  <l>Preach Chriſt the Way, the Truth, and Life in all,</l>
                  <l>With Holineſs thy Doctrine Sounds to Men,</l>
                  <l>That they might know and live in Gods great Call,</l>
                  <l>Thy Work is done, and thou art now at Reſt,</l>
                  <l>And all thy Labour in this World doth ceaſe:</l>
                  <l>The Wiſe in Heart will ſay that thou art Bleſt,</l>
                  <l>And pray to God ſuch Prophets may increaſe,</l>
                  <l>With blameleſs Life thou didſt Truth's Cauſe maintain,</l>
                  <l>And out of that which might defile didſt live,</l>
                  <l>As Bleſſed Man, didſt Holineſs retain,</l>
                  <l>And unto God all Honour thou didſt give.</l>
                  <l>The Lord who doth the Saved People Bleſs,</l>
                  <l>He was thy Peace, thy Comfort and thy All,</l>
                  <l>Much was the Gift Chriſt gave thee to poſſeſs,</l>
                  <l>Which thou didſt uſe as he for it did Call.</l>
                  <l>Much could I ſay, if I to Write were free,</l>
                  <l>Of many things which did attend thy Life,</l>
                  <l>But Silence ſhall Apologize for me,</l>
                  <l>As one that loves and lives above all Strife.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>John Raunce.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>The <hi>20th.</hi> Day of the laſt Month in the Year 1682.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:101079:18"/>
               <head>Something added by another Friend, of that Antient in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> J. S. Deceaſed.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>IN Chriſt that is the</hi> Alpha, <hi>all in all,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>O mega <hi>th' Laſt, from Death to Life doth call.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>How Holy, Harmleſs, Sweet then is that Man,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nought but thy Lord give Satisfaction can:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Some things both Old and New they are but vain,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Truth 'gainſt Tradition well thou didſt maintain;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Of Innovation thou Prophetick ſaw,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Rules made by Men laſt turned into Law,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Yet Truth reſiſt's hence Church Diviſions grow,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hence Perſecutions flow,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hence Goſpel Teachings put a stop unto.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>J. C.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="testimony">
               <head>
                  <hi>Charles Harris</hi> his Teſtimony.</head>
               <p>AS for <hi>John Story,</hi> he bore the Countenance of a Man of God, and was a Preacher of Righteouſneſs in his Day, both in Doctrine and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, and as ſuch was eſteemed by thouſands for many years: yet he went not to his Grave under that Sentence, <hi>Viz. Wo to you when all Men ſpeak well of you.</hi> For he met with ſuch Exerciſe as Holy <hi>Paul</hi> did, from ſome that could once have pull'd out their Eyes to Serve him, afterwards be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came his Enemies, ſaying, <hi>his Speech was Centemptible,</hi> ſeeking a Proof of Chriſt ſpeaking in him: and he had ſome ſhare with that Beloved Diſciple, that ſaith in his Epiſtle to <hi>Gaius</hi> on this wiſe, <hi>Viz. I wrote unto the Church, but</hi> Diotrephes, <hi>who loveth to have the Preheminence among them, Receiveth us not, prating againſt us with malitious Words; and not content therewith; neither doth he himſelf Receive the Brethren, and forbiddeth them that would, and caſteth them out of the Church</hi> (or declared out of Unity) <hi>or thruſt out of the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation:</hi>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:101079:19"/> I have known him for many years, and never found but that he was a Man of Peace: it hath been frequently reported he was a <hi>Tyth-Payer:</hi> Let the Reader obſerve, he never ſtood in ſuch a Capacity all his Days, never Keeping Houſe, or Occupying any Land (being a Single Man) and as to his Judgment concerning <hi>Tythes,</hi> it may be ſeen in what follows, under his own hand: So whether it be better to Judge of a Man by his own Words and Deeds, or by ones own Imaginations called Senſe, let the Charitable Reader Judge.</p>
               <p>He has alſo been termed, <hi>Of a Dividing Spirit.</hi> Let his Epiſtle ſpeak for himſelf; ſome ſay his Miniſtry was dead; which I ſay, if they had lived in that time that the Diſciple <hi>John</hi> was led to the Church, and ſaid not much more, but, <hi>Little Children, love one another:</hi> it may be they would have ſaid <hi>he was Dead and Formal.</hi> It is to be obſerved <hi>J. S.</hi> was much ſpent before his Departure, having been a Preacher from his Youth, ſo had not ſtrength of Voice to utter himſelf as formerly, but ſtill what he ſaid was of this tenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, <hi>Viz. That if Friends did believe in and wait upon God, in the Manifeſtation of our Lord Chriſt, he would in due time anſwer all the Immortal Longings of their Souls, and preſerve them to his Glory and Kingdom.</hi> And indeed to them that loved him, he was in their Eye the ſame Man to his death that he had been all along, ſtill growing in the ſame Truth.</p>
               <p>And as for the Diviſions that ſprang up both <hi>North</hi> and <hi>South;</hi> it is well known that it was not he that cauſed them: I well remember how it was <hi>Weſtward,</hi> till ſome Perſons went that way, and ſtirred up the People into Parties; one Day they will feel the Burthen of it.</p>
               <p>In what follows there are two <hi>Queries</hi> propoſed to Friends at <hi>Drawell.,</hi> with their <hi>Anſwers.</hi> If all would but keep to it accordingly, there would be no Strife: and as for that way that is taken by ſome to defame every man, by endeavouring to take away his Good Name, both as a Man and Chriſtian, that is not Conformable to ſome new ſort of Church-Government and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline (ſo called) Though for a time they may ſeem to Reign as Kings upon Earth, they ſhall dye like Men; and it ſhall be known in the end, that the Peace of the Church, and Love to Brethren, is of more value than all <hi>Sounding Braſs</hi> or <hi>Tincling Cymbals.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So bleſſed are all ſuch true Preachers that look upwards for their Reward in that World that is to come. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>C. H.</signed> As to what follows, if thou canſt believe that Men mean as they ſpeak, Read on, if not, ſtay till thou haſt Charity.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="questions">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:101079:19"/>
               <head>Two Queſtions propoſed by <hi>J. W.</hi> and <hi>J. S.</hi> to Friends of the Meeting at <hi>Drawell;</hi> and their Anſwers, <hi>Viz.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="question">
                  <head>Queſtion I.</head>
                  <p>WHether or no, we, and all Gods People ought not to be left, in all Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Faith and Diſcipline (ſo far as Diſcipline may become Matter of Faith) to the Manifeſtation of Gods Spirit and Truth in our own Hearts, and to ſpeak and act therein as we are thereby Inſtructed and Perſwaded, and not otherwiſe?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="question">
                  <head>Queſtion II.</head>
                  <p>2dly. <hi>Since there are Diverſities of Talents and Gifts given by the Spirit of God, and received by Men: Whether the Judgment of Truth it ſelf given forth through a Part of the Members of Chriſt's Body, can become a Bond upon any other Part of the ſaid Body, further than their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandings are illuminated thereby?</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>To the firſt Queſtion we ſay, <hi>Yea;</hi> and <hi>Nay</hi> to the ſecond Queſtion, with that true and ſimple Senſe that the Words import, and Friends have been uſed to underſtand them: but not to ſtrengthen Prejudiced Spirits, who have made that their Plea for their Separation, and againſt Truths Authority in our <hi>Monthly</hi> and <hi>Quarterly Meetings;</hi> nor yet to Juſtifie any that are Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, through their own Sloth and Unfaithfulneſs; or to excuſe them, that would not be accounted Weak, but Strong, Wiſe, and as Pillars.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="judgment">
               <head>The Judgment of <hi>J. W.</hi> and <hi>J. S.</hi> concerning the Five Heads on which the 44 Articles exhibited againſt them, were grounded, which was pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly read in the Meeting at <hi>Drawell,</hi> as followeth.</head>
               <p>ON the whole Matter, in the Fear and Preſence of the Almighty God we declare, That we do approve of <hi>Monthly</hi> and <hi>Quarterly Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> for the neceſſary Service of the Truth; ſo we farther ſay, that as thoſe, or any other Meetings of Friends in Truth, ſhall be continued to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:101079:20"/> anſwer thoſe Services; we believe, that as it now is, it alſo will become our Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to be at Unity with our Brethren in the Services thereof; and that though one of us, <hi>Viz. J. W.</hi> did condeſcend to Subſcribe to a Paper, for the Erecting a <hi>Womans-Meeting</hi> in the Country, to anſwer the ends the Paper propoſed; which he teſtifies he then did in ſingleneſs of Heart, for Unity-Sake; yet ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that inward ſenſe we now have, there appears to us no abſolute ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity to continue <hi>Womens-Meetings,</hi> in the Country diſtinct and ſeparate from the Men; and therefore do Conſcientiouſly forbear to aſſent or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage any to lay the Intents of Marriages before them; yet that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Senſe and Heavenly Underſtanding we have received from God, hath, and yet doth confirm us in this Judgment, that 'tis not agreeable with the Line of Truth, to oppoſe others in the Exerciſe and appointed Service of the ſaid Meetings as heretofore, and now are ſettled and agreed upon, who being Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious therein, are otherwiſe Minded than we are: and if any of our Words or Actions have had any tendency to oppoſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which we are not Conſcious of, but if we were, would readily confeſs; and we ſay, the Truth in us would readily have condemned it, even as it now doth; and if it ſhall pleaſe the Lord to manifeſt unto us a Service in thoſe Meetings in the Country, as well as City, the ſame Integrity towards God which hath dwelt in us theſe many years paſt, we believe will become a Bond on us to joyn Hand and Heart with others our Brethren and Siſters therein; but till then, our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires are, that this may not become an Occaſion of ſtraitneſs in Spirit each to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the other, but that embracing the wholeſome Counſel of the Apoſtle in another Caſe, (<hi>If in any thing ye are otherwiſe Minded, wait till God reveal it</hi>) we may walk together in that pure undefiled Love of our God, which think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no Evil.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>2dly.</hi> That though many of our Brethren ſee a Service in Recording Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnations, and leaving them upon Record to Poſterity: yet from that inward Sence and Heavenly Underſtanding we have, we ſee no neceſſity to leave them upon Record to Poſterity, or retain them when the Sin is blotted out and remitted by the Lord, neither to be extended farther than the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence is known, nor yet to continue longer than the memory of the Offence abideth; but if any ſee meet from an inward ſenſe of the Truth in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, to leave ſuch a Teſtimony relating to themſelves to Poſterity, we have therewith Unity. That this our ſenſe may be no occaſion of ſtraitneſs of Spirit each toward the other, is the earneſt deſire of our Souls, who deſire the Proſperity of Truth and Peace amongſt all the Churches of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>3dly.</hi> As to <hi>Tythes,</hi> we can in truth ſay, 'twas never ſo much as in our thoughts to ſpeak any words whatſoever, with the leaſt intent to ſtrengthen any in the Payment thereof, nor yet to weaken the Faith of any, having a teſtimony in our hearts, that <hi>Tythes</hi> as at this Day paid, are Antichriſtian.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:101079:20"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>4thly.</hi> That as Groanings, Sighings, Soundings and Singings may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from Deceitful Spirits, ſo alſo we declare, Groanings, Sighings, Soundings, and Singing may be the Fruit of the Spirit of the Lord among Gods People: and that as the firſt is diſcouraged, the ſecond ought to be incouraged: and the earneſt Deſire of our ſoul is, that as to theſe things, nothing but the Spirit of Truth and Sound Judgment may appear, either to reprove or Incourage; and though we are accuſed as if we were Oppoſers of ſuch Groanings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which the Truth approved, yet God is our Witneſs, we know it not.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>5thly.</hi> That though we have been repreſented as Perſons incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging Flying in time of Perſecution: We ſay, we are not Conſcious to our ſelves of ſo doing: for we believe thoſe who ſtand not to their Teſtimony, but flyes therefrom in the Day of Perſecution, may truly be counted, either weak in Faith, or departed from the Faith.</p>
               <p>And thus having given our Inward Sence, according to the Uprightneſs and Integrity of our Hearts, concerning theſe five General Heads, from whence all the 44 Articles do ariſe: We ſhall with this conclude, That the God of Heaven is our Witneſs, our Deſires are to approve our ſelves Men of Peace, in the Abhorrency of all Fleſhly Liberty and Looſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to follow after Truth and Righteouſneſs, that the Reign of the Power of the Eternal God may be over all; ſo will the Kingdoms of this World be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Kingdoms of the Lord and his Chriſt.</p>
               <p>As to the two <hi>Queſtions</hi> anſwered by the Friends and Brethren, met on this Occaſion, we in the Fear of the Lord ſay, We in the propoſing thereof, had not the leaſt thought to obtain your <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>Nay,</hi> with intent thereby to ſtrengthen ſuch who may be accounted our Party, in any thing that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Truth, nor to incourage Looſeneſs or Bad Spirits, but Conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to remove the Scruples of ſome: and further we ſay, we are better ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with your Explication therein, than with your bear <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>Nay;</hi> for we, as well as you, are ſenſible <hi>Apoſtates</hi> and <hi>Bad Spirits,</hi> ſeekinga Fleſhly Liberty, have made uſe of Arguments deducible from ſuch Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Truth, to oppoſe the Power of God it ſelf, and the Practice af Gods People in the Power.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <list>
                        <item>John Wilkinſon</item>
                        <item>John Story,</item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="epistle">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:101079:21"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>John Story</hi>'s Epiſtle to Friends in the <hi>North,</hi> in which is ſignified his Deſires for true Unity and Reconciliation.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Friends,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>IN the Love of God and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, which is Holy and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable for ever, do I Salute you. The Occaſion of my Writing at this time is to let you know, that my Soul hath been deeply exerciſed from day to day, in the inward Conſiderations that have been with me for ſome time: how the Holy Name of God is Blaſphemed, and the Profeſſion of his Truth diſhonoured among Unbelievers, by the Reports that are ſpread abroad amongſt them of the Diviſions that are amongſt us, who have in ſcorn been called <hi>Quakers,</hi> and alſo for the hurt and havock that I perceive is at this day made amongſt the Heritage of God, through this ſecret and ſubtil working of the Antient Enemy of Mankind, who at this day, as in days paſt, hunts to and fro, ſeeking whom he may deſtroy.</p>
               <p>Now foraſmuch as there hath been great Diſcourſes amongſt Friends touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a <hi>Separate Spirit</hi> and <hi>Meeting</hi> in the <hi>North;</hi> meaning thereby, a <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Meeting</hi> that is Separate from the Truth, and that I have been a ſtrength to ſuch a <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Meeting.</hi> I have this to ſay, that the Searcher of all hearts knows I own no ſuch <hi>Spirit</hi> or <hi>Meeting</hi> that is Separate from the Truth, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have I ever been a Setter up or Actor in any ſuch <hi>Meeting;</hi> for though I am accuſed, that the Subſcription of my Name to a Paper amongſt others, entitules me to be a Setter up of a <hi>Separate Meeting:</hi> yet I am not in my Conſcience convinced there is any one Word therein which juſtly entitles me to be a Setter up of the <hi>Meeting</hi> called, <hi>a Separate Meeting.</hi> For the Paper of Propoſals I Signed, was intended to Re-unite that <hi>Meeting;</hi> and I am perſwaded, all Underſtanding Men that Signed, did it for that End; and if any thing therein had ſeemed to them too ſtrait, why did not they to whom it was ſent deſire a loving Diſcourſe about it, that they might have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood our meaning before they had either replyed or ſent it abroad, in which we ſhould have been ready to have given our ſence more fully, which ſeveral have already done; and though I have been by ſome abuſively called a <hi>Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain;</hi>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:101079:21"/> the Lord is my Witneſs, my deſire neither hath been, nor is, to be a <hi>Captain</hi> over any, to the Praiſe of the Lord I ſpeak it; I have learned the Truth of our Lord Jeſus better than ſo; for I know him that is the Captain of our Salvation ought to be the alone Leader of his People: and the earneſt breathing of my Soul is, that as for many years paſt I have approved my ſelf to the Friends of Truth the Lords Servant; ſo I may to the end of my days, and that for Chriſt's ſake; and therefore can I with boldneſs ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to Gods Witneſs in all Conſciences, whether an Inſinuation into the Breſts of any, that I am a Strenth to ſuch a <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Meeting</hi> as aforeſaid, be not the Work of the Old Enemy.</p>
               <p>And ſince 'tis ſo, that I have been credibly informed, that you who former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Aſſembled together in one Meeting to manage the Outward Concerns of Truth relating to the Poor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> have, for ſome time paſt, Aſſembled for the aforeſaid Service in two diſtinct Meetings, and that this is accounted an Occaſion of Stubling to ſome. I have a Concern on my Spirit thus to write unto you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> I am ſatisfied in my Conſcience from ſufficent Knowledge or Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that the Day was, wherein you met together in a Sweet Union and Fellowſhip, to manage the Outward Concerns of Truth relating to the Poor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> That ſuch your Union and Fellowſhip had acceptance with the Lord, and was owned by his Preſence amongſt you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That during ſuch your Fellowſhip, every one concerned in that Service, acted from a ready and willing Mind, according to that Perſwaſion and Manifeſtation which was given of God, without being Impoſed upon by any Man or Men, or endeavouring to Impoſe each on other, contrary to what the Lord Evidenced by his Spirit in your Conſciences.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> That though it was ſo, that particular Perſons, in perſuance of the Counſel of divers Antient and Honourable Brethren (ſome of whom are fallen aſleep) were choſen for that Service of the Poor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> out of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Meetings held for the Worſhip of God, yet I never underſtood that any deſigned to exclude any Member or Members of the Church of Chriſt, (who had, or might have a Concern upon their Spirits) from Sitting or Acting amongſt them, whil'ſt any ſuch Member or Members (though not chozen) behaved themſelves Men of Peace, good Order, and in Unity with the Faithful Friends chozen for the Management of the Affairs of the Truth relating to the Poor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in ſuch Meeting; and as in Charity I dare not reflect on theſe Antient Brethren in whoſe Advice for the holding ſuch Meetings, there ſeems to be room for <hi>Cavelling Spirits</hi> to call them <hi>Narrow-Spirited,</hi> in adviſing to thoſe certain Perſons for that Service, which ſeems a kind of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation: yet I am alſo ſatisfied that thoſe Antient Brethren, who firſt advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to chooſe Faithful Brethren for the aforeſaid Service, would have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured an excluſion of all ſuch (if any ſuch had then been) who ſhould from
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:101079:22"/> time to time have appeared as diſorderly Troublers of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and Impoſers on Tender Conſciences.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> That though it hath been reported, that thoſe of you who are by ſome called a <hi>Separate Meeting,</hi> have been ſo <hi>Narrow Spirited,</hi> as that you will not joyn with the Brethren in the aforeſaid Service, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> unleſs they will aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent that others not formerly chozen, may be excluded from acting with you, or if they have ought to offer to the Meeting, then to be admitted to offer the ſame, and ſo depart: which Report, as it is ſaid, is grounded on a Paper Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by ſeveral of you, and my ſelf, and is by ſome accounted the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the aforeſaid Meeting, called the <hi>Seprate Meeting;</hi> yet I always un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood that it was not intended by any of the Subſcribers, to exclude any from Sitting amongſt you, or Joyning with you in the Common Service of Truth, uſually tranſacted amongſt you in the Spirit of Love and Unity, who in the ſame Spirit of Love and Unity would accompany you, and had a Concern to add a helping hand: and this ſenſe I do now ſolemnly declare to be my ſenſe, and that at the time I Signed the Paper aforeſaid, it was my ſence; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther am I yet convicted, that if the Subſcribers of the ſaid Paper interpret for themſelves (which of right they have the liberty to do) there is any thing therein contained which doth oppoſe the ſame ſenſe.</p>
               <p>Now Friends, I have this further to ſay, that I have more than ordinary ground either to know, or at leaſt believe, that this my ſenſe in the aforeſaid five Particulars, is the real &amp; true State of the Caſe, but do certainly know, that it contains in ſome meaſure, the State of Truth, as it ought to have been amongſt you; and therefore my Counſel and Exhortation to you is, laying aſide all <hi>vain Janglings</hi> and <hi>Repititions of former Things,</hi> that have tended to <hi>Strife</hi> and <hi>Debate,</hi> contrary to the Truth, ye be Reconciled each unto the other in the Lord, ſaying in your Hearts before the Lord, and in his Fear, <hi>Let the Time paſt be ſufficient, and for time to come let us ſtudy Peace, and Aſſemble to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the Antient Chriſtian Love, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion and Fellowſhip which was amongſt us before the Occaſion or Offences were either given or taken, and that you Unite and Meet together to manage the Outward Concerns of Truth relating to the Poor,</hi> &amp;c. With this Godly Unanimous Intention of Heart, that if for the future any ſhall come in amongſt you, and appear as diſorderly Troublers of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> contentious Perſons in Matters not approved by you, and the Aſſemblies of Gods People amongſt you, or Impoſers upon tender Conſciences contrary to what hath been Received, Believed and Owned by you and the Aſſemblies of Gods People amongſt you, when you and they were preſerved in a ſweet Union and Fellowſhip in the Truth; you then declare that ſuch Perſons are not worthy to ſit among you to act in the Affairs of Truth, and that upon a ſerious and godly acknowledgment unto this Sound and Certain Truth, <hi>That all Gods People ought to be left, in all Matters of Faith and Diſcipline, ſo far as the Diſcipline becomes Matter of Faith, to the Manifeſtation of Gods Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:101079:22"/> &amp; Truth in their own Hearts, and to ſpeak and act therein as they ſhall be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Inſtructed and Perſwaded, and not otherwiſe; becauſe ſince there are diverſities of Talents and Gifts given by the Spirit of God, and received by Men, the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Truth it ſelf given forth through a part of the Members of Chriſts Body, cannot become a Bond upon any other part of the ſaid Body, further than their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings come to be Illuminated thereby.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Sound and Certain Truth, unto which I exhort your ſerious and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Acknowledgment, I and many, if not all of you do know, was at the Meeting at <hi>Drawell</hi> fully aſſented to, to be Truth, and that by an Anſwer to two Queſtions, wherein it was fully Stated, and rightly Anſwered; and therefore ſince I am truly ſenſible, that the Cauſe of your Differences hath ſprung from that which hath led from this Sound and certain Truth; I may reaſonably expect that my Counſel to Re-unite may have place with you.</p>
               <p>Thus it is with me to write unto you, and that the more freely too, becauſe there are ſome do apprehend that I am more capable to Re-unite you, than ſome others are, who now may ſee my Endeavours are not wanting, and that as I have approved my ſelf a Man of Peace, ſo my Deſires are, that the Peace of God in the Love and Unity of the Truth, may abound amongſt you.</p>
               <p>And now Friends, I ſhall leave it to the Righteous God to Judge, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther what is now propoſed be not according to the Spirit of Truth, which by its appearance in every Member of the Church of Chriſt at this day, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the only Lawgiver in every ſuch Member in Matters that relate to the World to come, for by it we are inſtructed in our Heavenly Duties to God, <hi>Viz.</hi> How to Sacrifice, to Worſhip, and Serve him acceptably by Obedience to all his Requirings; and through the ſame are the Lords People led into ſuch Methods or Outward Practices wherein they are helpful and Serviceable each to other in their Generation, for the Lord alone ought to be ey'd in, and beyond Outward Forms, though his Preſence hath been, and ſtill is with his People in thoſe Forms he leads into; and ſo to him let us look, who was before all Time and Days of this Fading World, and is the <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> the Beginner and Finiſher of the Work of our Redemption, which was, and which is, and which is to come, the Almighty, who alone ought to be minded beyond all viſible Things, and unto him in all our Exerciſes, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Inward or Outward, my Soul deſires we may all be kept, even in that Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Appearance of our Lord and Saviour, which is that acceptable Day which ſhines in the Inward Man, through which God hath made me, amongſt many other of his Servants, partaker of that Heavenly Religion which is unſpotted: many of you know our Beginning was in his Holy Spirit and Power, through which Death is, and ſhall be more fully aboliſhed, and Life and Immortality brought to Light, in and through which Power alone the Saints have, and ſhall be throughly Sanctified and Perfected for ever; and through it, are the Heirs of that Eternal Inheritance and Heavenly King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:101079:23"/> which outlaſts all Outward Things, and never fadeth away, where all the Longings, Earnings, and Deſires of the Righteous ſhall be fully Anſwered and Satisfied for evermore, with the full Injoyment of that Life and Immortality, over which the Second Death hath no Dominion; and then may it be truly ſaid of ſuch, <hi>That they are entred in and do take their Poſſeſſions.</hi> Now into this Life, in which the Heavenly Brotherhood and Fellowſhip of Saints ſtand, the Lord gather you all more and more, that whatever hath appeared in any contrary thereto, may by his Word of Life be broken down, ſubdued, and riſe no more, that into the Bond of Peace and Union in the Truth ye may be again United, and become Co-workers together, as Gods Heavenly Family in the Love, even in that Love which thinks no Evil; for the Deſire of my Soul is, that ye may be cemented and Eſtabliſhed together upon that Everlaſting Rock and Foundation which the Gates of Hell and Death can never prevail againſt.</p>
               <p>I ſhall now conclude with thoſe wholeſome words of the Apoſtle, of our Lord and Saviour: <hi>Put on therefore as the Elect of God, Holy and Beloved, Bowels of Mercies, Kindneſs, Humbleneſs of Mind, Meekneſs, Long-Suffering, Forbearing one another: if any Man have a Quarrel againſt any, even as Chriſt forgave you, even ſo do ye; and above all theſe Things put on Charity, which is the Bond of Perfectneſs; and let the Peace of God Rule in your Hearts, to the which you are called.</hi> Col. 3. 12. So in the Deſire to the Lord God, that theſe things may truly be weighed, and have place with you. I reſt,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Servant in the Work and Labour of the Goſpel <hi>John Story.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <head>POST-SCRIPT.</head>
                  <p>LET this Epiſtle be read in an Aſſembly to be appointed for both Meetings, <hi>Viz.</hi> that called <hi>Quarterly,</hi> and that called <hi>Separate,</hi> in or near <hi>Kendal,</hi> for my earneſt Deſire is, that it ſhould be ſo Read, becauſe, as I ſaid before, I have a Concern upon my Spirit thus to write unto you both; the things therein Contained I Recommend to Gods Witneſs in all your Conſciences, not deſiring to Impoſe on any; I know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this, that where it is awakened, there will be an Anſwer to the Spirit of Peace and Truth in which 'twas wrote; and though ſome have given forth their falſe Cenſures, and falſe Propheſies concerning me, and others laid various Temptations before me, which I look upon to be the Work of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:101079:23"/> the Common Enemy, that ſo I might have Stumbled and Fallen (though thoſe in whom it hath ſo wrought, may not have an Eye open to ſee it) yet my Joy and Rejoycing in the Lord is, that they have not yet removed me from the hope of the Goſpel, Bleſſed be the Name of God for ever more, for to his Praiſe and Glory, and in his Fear (which hitherto hath Preſerved me) I ſpeak it, my Cryes the Lord hath heard, and he hath given me a certain Knowledge of his Way, otherwiſe I might have been in great Danger to have ſunk into the Pit of Confuſion, and never riſen more: but his Love is unchangeable, his Mercy never fails them that put their Truſt in him; this by long Experience can I now Speak; therefore I exhort and intreat you all to turn your Minds to his Inward Appearance, through which his Love, which is ſtronger than Death, will be ſhed abroad in your Hearts, and his Power be felt, which will remove that which hath been the Cauſe of your Breach, that you may come again to walk together in that Heavenly Charity, through which no former Miſcarriage will be remembred, and ſo come to Serve him with one Heart, in that way of Life which he hath made known unto us in theſe latter Days: and thus you may finiſh your Courſe with Joy, and leave this World in Peace and Injoyment of Immortality, and take your Poſſeſſions in that Kingdom, in which the Fulneſs of Joy that ever ſhall be, is Inherited, and where, through the Earneſt and Aſſurance of the Heavenly Kingdom, the laſt End of the Righteous is Crowned with Honour; and in that Day the many Temptations that have, and do attend Gods People in this Fading Life, ſhall ceaſe, and never be again.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>J. S.</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Calne,</hi> 
                        <date>the laſt of the <hi>7th.</hi> Month, 1677.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>And at preſent, for a Concluſion, we Thus End.</head>
               <p>NOw as to all ſuch that have, or yet may think to defame us, by ſaying in a proud ſcoffing manner, <hi>Theſe are</hi> Storians, <hi>or of</hi> Story'<hi>s Spirit:</hi> we know nothing that he either held or practiſed (on a Religious Account) but what was agreeable to the Holy Scriptures, and the Teſtimony of Gods Spirit, as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived amongſt us in the Beginning, ſo he is gone to his Grave,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:101079:24"/> no <hi>Sect-Maſter,</hi> but a Follower of Chriſt: and we never deſire to follow him, nor any Man, but in the Steps and Way of that Stable Truth that ſhall outlaſt all New Inventions, and Envious Nick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Names.</p>
               <p>And although for a time the multitude of <hi>Iſrael</hi> did give their <hi>Ear-rings,</hi> or <hi>Jewels</hi> of Prey to <hi>Giddion</hi> to make a Golden <hi>Ephod,</hi> and ſaid, he ſhould Rule over them; the Evil Snare and Shame it af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards brought upon them and him, might be a Warning to others. <hi>Giddions</hi> Beginning was Glorious and wonderfull; but when the Hearts of that People began to turn from the Lord, they tempted <hi>Giddion,</hi> &amp; they were ſuffered to be a Snare to one another.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Page 8. Line laſt but 2, for <hi>of trouble,</hi> read, of the trouble. p. 11. l. 22. f. <hi>as Friends,</hi> r. all Friends. p. 12. l. 16. f. <hi>and as ſome,</hi> r. as ſome. l. 39. f. <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers at,</hi> r. Oppoſers of or at. p. 13. l. 29. f. <hi>amongſt you,</hi> r. againſt you. p. 19. l. 15. f. <hi>are we,</hi> r. we are. p. 26. l. 33. f <hi>even</hi> r. evil: p. 28. l. 1. f. <hi>Keep's</hi> r. Keyes. <hi>and the Folio to be made</hi> 28. p. 32. l. 3. f. <hi>one,</hi> r. own. l. 33. f. <hi>now</hi> r. nor. l. 43. f. <hi>thy years,</hi> r. the year.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:101079:24"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
